INTERVIEWER: Today is August 23, 2011.
采访者：今天是 2011 年 8 月 23 日。
I'm Chris Boebel.
我是 Chris Boebel。
As part of the MIT150 Infinite History project, we're talking
作为“麻省理工学院 150 年无限历史项目” 的一部分，我们正在与
with professor Hal Abelson.
Hal Abelson 教授进行访谈。
Professor Abelson is the Class of 1922 professor of
Abelson 教授是麻省理工学院（MIT）1922
electrical engineering and computer science at MIT.
（原文如此）届电气工程与计算机科学教授。
He holds an AB degree from Princeton University and a PhD
他拥有普林斯顿大学的文学学士学位和麻省理工学院
degree in mathematics from MIT.
的数学博士学位。
In 1992, Abelson was designated as one of MIT's six
1992 年，Abelson 被任命为麻省理工学院首批六位
inaugural MacVicar Faculty Fellows.
MacVicar 教师研究员之一。
Professor Abelson is co-director of the
Abelson 教授是 MIT-微软 iCampus
MIT-Microsoft iCampus Research Alliance in educational
教育技术研究联盟的
technology.
联合主任。
He's co-chair of the MIT Council on Educational
他是麻省理工学院教育技术委员会（MIT Council on Educational Technology）
Technology.
的共同主席。
And he serves on the steering committee
同时也在惠普-麻省理工学院（HP-MIT）
of the HP-MIT Alliance.
联盟的指导委员会任职。
He has played key roles in fostering MIT institutional
他在推动麻省理工学院的院校倡议中发挥了关键
initiatives such as MIT OpenCourseWare and DSpace.
作用，例如 MIT OpenCourseWare 和 DSpace。
Hal, thanks very much for taking the time--
Hal，非常感谢您能抽出时间——
ABELSON: Sure.
ABELSON：没问题。
INTERVIEWER: --to talk today.
采访者：——参加今天的谈话。
So let's start at the beginning.
那么让我们从头开始吧。
ABELSON: The beginning?
ABELSON：从头开始？
INTERVIEWER: The beginning.
采访者：是的，从头开始。
Just start by telling me a little bit about where you
请先跟我聊聊您是在哪里长大的，
grew up and the early years?
以及早年的生活？
ABELSON: So the real early years, I grew up on a chicken
ABELSON：真正的早年时期，我是在新泽西州中部的
farm in central New Jersey.
一个养鸡场长大的。
My parents worked on the farm.
我的父母在农场工作。
My father later went and worked in the post office.
我父亲后来去了邮局工作。
I was the first one in my family to go to college,
我是家里第一个上大学的人，
although my parents were always very, very interested
但是我的父母一直对教育非常、非常
in education.
感兴趣。
My parents liked music, education.
我的父母喜欢音乐和教育。
I had an uncle who sort of was the college person, who worked
我有一位叔叔算是家里读过大学的人，他在
for Exxon and had a high level position there.
Exxon（埃克森公司）工作并担任高管。
So we always cared a lot about education.
所以我们一直非常重视教育。
I'm not quite sure where I glommed onto math and science.
我不太确定自己是从哪里开始迷上数学和科学的。
I remember when I was I guess 12 or 13, I decided I wanted
我记得大概在十二三岁的时候，我决定我想
to be a physicist, mostly because I
成为一名物理学家，主要是因为
think I liked the word.
我喜欢这个词。
But I didn't know what that was.
但我当时并不了解那究竟是什么。
I did sort of okay in school.
我在学校的表现还算可以。
When I talk to kids these days, I remind them that when
如今我和孩子们交谈时，会提醒他们，当我像
I was their age in seventh or eighth grade, I was getting
他们那么大，读七八年级的时候，我的数学成绩
D's in mathematics.
是 D。
In fact, like a lot of people who end up going into
事实上，就像许多最终进入计算机领域的人
computers, we are really bad at doing arithmetic.
一样，我们其实非常不擅长算术。
Someone once said the reason a lot of people go into
有人曾说，很多人进入计算机领域的
computers is to make up for their own
原因是为了弥补自己在
handicaps in doing that.
这方面的不足。
So I wasn't particularly good in any of those
所以早期我在这些科目上表现得并不
subjects early on.
是特别好。
And then about the time I got in high school, I started
然后大约到了上高中的时候，我开始变得擅长
being good at it.
这些了。
One of the things the school did, they hired somebody to
学校当时做的一件事是雇人来
help me learn calculus because of course our school did
教我微积分，因为我们学校当然没有这样的
nothing like that.
课程。
And I don't know, sort of grew a lot of interest in math and
然后不知怎的，我从那时起开始对数学和科学产生了
science from there.
浓厚的兴趣。
So at some point I said gee, I don't want to
所以在某个时刻，我说，哎呀，我不
be a physicist anymore.
再想当物理学家了。
I want to be a mathematician because I guess that word
我想成为一名数学家，因为我觉得这个词听起来
sounded better.
更棒。
And then I got into Princeton on a scholarship, which was
后来我拿了奖学金进入普林斯顿大学，那样很好，
nice because my family could never have afforded
因为我的家庭根本负担不起那样的
anything like that.
事情。
And did pretty well at Princeton.
我在普林斯顿表现得相当不错。
Started getting interested in a subject
我开始对一门叫作代数拓扑（algebraic
called algebraic topology.
topology）的学科产生兴趣。
And then got into MIT graduate school on that.
凭借这个研究方向，被 MIT 研究生院录取。
And ended up coming to graduate school at MIT mostly
最终决定来 MIT 读研，主要是因为我
because my wife and I were looking for places
和妻子当时在寻找两人都能去
we could both go.
的地方。
We weren't married then, but she was looking for a place
那时我们还没结婚，但她在找一个她能
where she could go.
去的地方。
She got into BU's School of Social Work.
她去了 BU（波士顿大学）的社会工作学院。
I got into MIT.
我去了 MIT。
MIT also had a draft deferment.
MIT 当时还提供兵役缓征。
So back in ancient days, one of the things that you wanted
所以在那个久远的年代，假如你担心被
to do was if you were worried that getting drafted to go to
征召参加越南战争，你想做的事情之一就是，
the Vietnam War, so MIT did something where I think
MIT 有个政策，应该是因为我
because I was teaching or something like that, there was
在做教学或类似的工作，你可以获得
a category of draft deferment you could get.
某类兵役缓征。
So we ended up coming to MIT.
所以我们最终来到了 MIT。
And MIT was just absolutely an fascinating place.
MIT 绝对是一个非常迷人的地方。
One of the nicest things, when I first showed up at MIT, we
最美好的事情之一是，当我刚来到 MIT 时，我们
lived in Westgate.
住在 Westgate。
And one of the great memories that we had of being in
在 Westgate 最棒的回忆之一就是俯瞰
Westgate was looking down over the field and at the other end
球场，在另一端，看到麻省大道（Mass
of the field, seeing the tear gas on Mass Ave. Because that
Ave.）上的催泪瓦斯。因为那是连
was the time when even MIT students
MIT 的学生都在抗议
were protesting stuff.
的时代。
They were protesting, for anybody who remembers, Draper
他们抗议的是，如果有人还记得的话，
Labs used to be called the Institute Labs.
Draper 实验室曾经叫学院实验室。
And there was a protest about how is it that on the MIT
抗议的内容是，为什么 MIT 的校园里，
campus, there was classified research related to the
会有与越南战争相关的
Vietnam War?
机密研究？
It was just sort of wonderful.
那真实挺奇妙的。
Just marvelous to be here and look through this thing.
人在这里，目睹这一切，真是不可思议。
And what do I remember of MIT?
我对 MIT 还有什么记忆呢？
I remember going up to the door on 77 Mass Ave. And gosh,
我记得走到麻省大道 77 号的大门前。天哪，
they were automatic doors.
那是自动门。
And coming from Princeton, which is an ivy covered--
我是从普林斯顿来的， 那里是常春藤覆盖的——
it's the last thing in the world you would ever
这是世界上你最没法想象到
imagine like that.
的东西。
And then there were these long, long halls.
然后就是这些长长的走廊。
And I always had these visions of getting on roller skates
我总是幻想穿着旱冰鞋滑过长廊、
and going down the halls these automatic doors.
穿过那些自动门的画面。
It was just a wild place.
那真是一个疯狂的地方。
It was all one building.
整个学院就是一栋连在一起的大楼。
I didn't know quite what to make of it.
我当时不知道该怎么理解它。
But then early on, it could have been a couple of weeks
但是不久之后，可能是我到这里几周后，学生争取
after I got here, the Students for a Democratic Society, if
民主社会组织（Students for a Democratic Society），如果
anyone remembers that from the '60s, that was the campus
还有人记得 60 年代那会，那是当时的
activist organization.
校园激进组织。
It took over the President's Office.
它占领了校长办公室。
And they did this great thing.
他们干了件很棒的事情。
They had open house at the President's Office.
他们在校长办公室搞了个开放日。
And they were sitting there replaying the tapes so they
他们坐在那儿重放磁带，这样就能看到
could see what was typed on the electric typewriters in
Howard Johnson 校长办公室里的电动打字
President Howard Johnson's office.
机上打了什么。
And they held open house.
而且还举行了开放日。
And I said, hey, I'm a new graduate student.
我想，嘿，我是新入学的研究生。
I'm never in my life, ever going to be able to walk into
我这辈子都不会有机会走进 MIT
the MIT's President's Office.
的校长办公室。
So let me go sit around and see what's in
所以让我去坐坐，看看校长办公室
the President's Office.
里都有什么。
So we walk in.
所以我们走了进去。
And there were a bunch of students kind of sitting on
有一群学生就坐在校长
the floor of the President's Office.
办公室的地板上。
And I see a guy that I'd been to high school with, who I
我看到一个以前一起上高中的人，我知道他
knew had gone to MIT, but we'd had no contact since then.
去了 MIT，但后来就没有联系过了。
And I went up to him and said hi.
我走过去向他打招呼。
Gee, hi, Ronnie.
哎呀，嗨，Ronnie。
This is sort of really nice.
这真是太巧了。
And he says, what are you doing?
他说，你来做什么？
And I said, I'm a new graduate student.
我说，我是新来的研究生。
I'm looking for what to do.
我在找事情做。
What's interesting to do around here?
这儿有什么有意思的事情可以做吗？
And he said, oh, why don't you go over to the Artificial
他说，哦，你不去人工智能实验室（Artificial Intelligence Lab）
Intelligence Lab.
看看吗？
I hear they're doing interesting stuff.
我听说他们在做一些有意思的事情。
So I wandered over there and talked to some people.
于是我溜达过去，和一些人聊了聊。
And that's essentially how I got into computer science and
基本上，这就是我如何进入计算机科学、人工智能（AI）领域，
AI and all the stuff I'm doing now.
以及我现在所做的一切的。
And I like to tell that story to students who worry about
我喜欢把这个故事讲给那些担心长大后
what they're going to do when they grow up.
要做什么的学生听。
Because I like to tell them it will be random,
因为我想告诉他们，一切都是随机的，
and you have no idea.
你根本无法预料。
But at some point, some totally random thing will
但在某个时候，会发生一些完全随机
happen that will have a tremendous influence.
的事情，并产生巨大的影响。
So don't worry about it too much.
所以不要太担心。
INTERVIEWER: So backing up for just a moment, had you done
采访者：那么稍微回溯一下，你在那之前在普林斯顿，
work in computer science before that at Princeton, or
甚至更早之前，做过计算机科学方面
even previously?
的工作吗？
How did you first--
你最初是怎么——
ABELSON: Yeah.
ABELSON：对的。
At Princeton I did--
在普林斯顿，我——
well, there sort of wasn't a computer science major then.
呃，那时候还没有计算机科学专业。
In fact, I'm not even sure there was one at MIT
其实，我都不确定我当初来到 MIT 时有
when I showed up.
没有这个专业。
But at Princeton, a bunch of us worked in
但在普林斯顿，我们一群人在
the computer center.
计算机中心工作。
And the Princeton Computer Center had an IBM--
普林斯顿计算机中心有一台 IBM ——
I think a 7.090 or 7.10.
应该是 7.090 或 7.10。
It got one of the first 3.60s.
它搞到了最早的 3.60 之一。
And they were working on this very weird
他们当时在研究一种非常奇怪的东西，
thing called time sharing.
叫作分时系统（time sharing）。
And a bunch of us went around and messed around with that
我们一群人在上面四处摆弄，捣鼓
and did what most of Princeton considered to be a totally
普林斯顿大多数人认为是完全不值得用计算机
worthless, stupid thing with computers, which is actually
做的蠢事——那就是用它进行
using it for text processing.
文本处理。
Because everyone knew that what computers were really for
因为那时众所周知，计算机真正的用途是
were solving big complicated equations.
求解复杂大型方程式。
And the computer center used to take down the system a
计算机中心以前每周会停机几个小时，
couple of hours each week and let those of us who wanted to
让我们那些想要瞎胡闹、浪费时间的
screw around and waste time, play with this
家伙去摆弄这种文本编辑
text editing thing.
玩意儿。
Get tremendous complaints from the astrophysics department
结果受到了天体物理学系的巨量投诉， 因为
because people had to stop trying to
他们被迫停下来对科学方程式
solve on science equations.
的求解尝试。
So I became one of the people who were
所以，我成了那些瞎鼓捣
messing around with that.
这东西的人之一。
And I became a little bit of a consultant, an undergraduate
我后来有点像顾问，读本科的计算机系统顾问，
consultant in the computer system, teaching people to
教人们把他们的程序从 FORTRAN 迁移
migrate their programs from FORTRAN to a language that IBM
到 IBM 和其他一些地方当时推崇的语言，
and a couple of other places were pushing then called PL/1,
叫作 PL/1，一个非常谦虚的名字，
a very modest name, Programming Language 1.
“编程语言 1”。
And this was supposed to be the be all and end all of the
在设想中，它应该是一个终极解决方案， 不再需要其它
new computer stuff.
的计算机创新了。
And there was a big move to say you should translate all
当时有一种趋势，主张你应该将所有的程序都
your programs into PL/1.
转换成 PL/1。
So I became one of what was called the PL/1 kids and would
所以我成了所谓的“PL/1 小子”之一，
consult with faculty in the other departments about how to
为其他部门的教职员工提供咨询，看怎么修改
modify their programs.
他们的程序。
So I had some stuff in computing and
所以我确实接触过一些计算方面的东西，
I knew about that.
也有所自知。
I knew very little about what I actually went into at MIT.
对于我后来在 MIT 真正从事的领域，我当时知之甚少。
But it was a background in computers, enough to walk into
但那段计算机背景足以让我走进 AI Lab
the AI Lab and do interesting things.
去做些有趣的事情。
INTERVIEWER: But at the time you came to MIT, initially
采访者：但你来 MIT 的时候，
there was not a sense that you would be
最初并没有感觉到你会朝那个
moving in that direction?
方向发展？
ABELSON: No, I was in the math department.
ABELSON：没有，我当时在数学系。
And I was a graduate student in the math department, became
我是数学系的研究生，之后在数学系
an instructor in the math department after that, and
担任讲师，后来才转向计算领域，
only moved into computing later on because some of the
因为我当时从事的一部分
work I was doing in topology was related
拓扑学（topology）工作与
to distributed computing.
分布式计算有关。
And then sort of the topology part of it atrophied and the
后来，拓扑学的部分逐渐退化， 计算
computing part of it grew.
的部分不断增长。
And eventually when into computer science.
最终我进入了计算机科学。
INTERVIEWER: So you mentioned the AI Lab.
采访者：你提到了 AI 实验室。
Talk a bit more about working there and also you worked with
多聊聊在那儿工作的情况，而且你还和 Seymour Papert
Seymour Papert in the Logo Lab as well, right?
在 Logo 实验室共事过，对吧？
ABELSON: Well, that's actually how I started in the AI Lab.
ABELSON：噢，那其实是我在 AI Lab 的起点。
For some reason I went--
出于某种原因，我去了——
there was an early Logo presentation called I think
当时有一场早期的 Logo 演示，我记得题目是《教孩子思考》
Teaching Children Thinking, which was in 26-100.
（Teaching Children Thinking），在 26-100 教室举行。
And it was this big thing where Seymour Papert and his
那是一场盛会，Seymour Papert 和他
assistant for many years, Cynthia Solomon, talked about
多年的助手 Cynthia Solomon 讲解 Logo
the Logo computer language and showed the Logo turtle.
计算机语言，并展示了 Logo 海龟。
And I looked at it and it was pretty fascinating.
我看到它，觉得非常迷人。
And pretty wild.
也非常大胆。
I remember later on reading a report from a journalist who's
我记得后来读到一位去过现场的记者的
been there.
报道。
And her mind was just blown about this notion that
她觉得大为震撼，对孩子们应该做这些
children should do these weird robot things.
奇怪的机器人玩意的想法。
And I remember her saying, I looked at this thing and I
我记得她说，看着这玩意儿，我觉得
thought these people were witches.
这群人是巫师。
But anyway, I thought they were cool, whether they were
但无论如何，不管他们是不是巫师，我觉得
witches or not.
他们很酷。
And I walked over to the AI Lab, looking for
于是我走到 AI 实验室，
something to do.
找点事情做。
And walked into the elevator.
然后我上了电梯。
And then elevator stopped at one of the floors and then
电梯停在了某一层，Seymour
Seymour got in.
走了进来。
And I said, hi, I like your stuff.
我说，嗨，我喜欢你做的东西。
I'm a new graduate student.
我是新来的研究生。
Can I work for you?
我能给你干活吗？
And he said, yeah.
他说，好啊。
And that's how I got into this whole business.
这就是我进入整个这些事情的经过。
So another bunch of random events.
所以又是一连串的随机事件。
INTERVIEWER: So you've talked a little bit about what it was
采访者：您刚才谈到了 1960 年代末来到
like coming to MIT in the late 1960s, what your impression
MIT 的情况，以及您
was of the campus.
对校园的印象。
But give me a little bit more information about sort of the
但请再多给我一些关于
culture and the environment at that time.
当时文化和环境的信息吧。
I mean obviously it differed as you've said from Princeton
我的意思是，正如您所说显然它与普林斯顿不同，
and was unlike other things you'd seen.
也与您见过的其他事物都不同。
ABELSON: Well to me, it was really strange.
ABELSON：嗯，对我来说，这真的很奇怪。
I mean MIT is such a big complicated place.
我是说，MIT 是一个如此庞大且复杂的地方。
I've often thought that well, after being here about 20
我经常想，在这里待了大约 20
years I finally got the ability to think of the place
年后，我才终于能把这里看作
as a whole place.
一个整体。
And I just don't even know how it's possible to do that
我甚至不知道如何才能做到这一点，
because there are just so many things going on and it's so
因为同时发生的事太多，
complicated.
太复杂了。
But my impression from Princeton is that it was very
但是从普林斯顿来的印象是，它非常
strange and very regimented.
奇怪，非常刻板。
So I remember hearing about the Experimental Study Group.
我记得听人说“实验学习小组” （Experimental Study Group，ESG）的时候。
So what people told me about the Experimental Study Group
他们告诉我，实验学习小组是
was that it was a place where you could learn on your own
一个你可以自学、
and do stuff that's independently
独立做事的地方，
and it was very open.
非常开放。
And I remember going over that, because I had some
我记得我去那边看了，因为我有
friends who were in the ESG.
一些朋友在 ESG 里。
So what do you do here?
“所以你们在这里做什么？”
What do you do that's independent?
“哪些事情是可以独立做的呢？”
And they said something like, well we get to take the
他们大概说，“嗯，我们可以修读
standard course curriculum, but we get
标准的课程大纲，但我们
to study it by ourselves.
可以自学。”
And I just remember breaking down laughing.
我就记得我当时笑惨了。
I said, that's this place's idea of what independent
我说，这就是这个地方对
learning is?
“独立学习”的理解吗？
Because I'd been in a program at Princeton, a very '60s
因为我曾参加过普林斯顿的一个项目，一个非常有
program, I think even Princeton stop doing it, where
60 年代特殊的项目，哪怕是普林斯顿也不这么干了，
they admitted you.
他们录取你。
And they said hey, you're a bunch of smart people.
然后说，嘿，你们是一群聪明人。
You have no requirements.
你们没有课程要求。
You had department requirements.
你们有系里的要求。
But the rest of the time, Princeton's a big place, take
但剩下的时间里，普林斯顿是个大地方，
what you want.
想学什么就学什么吧。
And all of the standard things you'd call distribution
所有那些所谓标准，比如通识要求、
requirements or university requirements are just
学校必修要求，对你们
abolished for you.
都取消了。
Some of us totally exploited it.
我们有些人把这点利用得相当彻底。
Some of us had a great time.
有些人过得非常愉快。
I ended up with a couple of friends essentially living as
我最终和几个朋友基本上是以研究生
graduate students in the math department.
的身份生活在数学系里。
But coming from there to MIT, it was this sense of being
但从那里来到 MIT，感受到的是严格
regimented and precise.
管理、精确规范。
Later I've come to identify that as
后来我逐渐将那认定为
an engineering culture.
一种工程文化。
I see the same thing happening at Google, because I've been
我在谷歌也看到了同样的情况，因为我
spending time at Google.
最近在 Google 待着。
So you see this culture and you love it.
所以你看到这种文化，而且会爱上它。
I mean I just love engineer's culture.
我的意思是，我真的很喜欢工程师文化。
I'm an engineer and I do that.
我是一个工程师，我就是这么做事的。
But one of the characteristics of an engineer's culture is
但工程文化有个特点：你会
you sort of sit and you say, what's the problem, what are
坐下来说，问题是什么，
you're trying to do?
你要做什么？
And then about three seconds later you say
然后大约三秒钟后你会说：
okay, what's the solution?
好吧，解决方案是什么？
And you think for about two minutes and you
然后你再想上两分钟，就把
figure out the solution.
解决方案想出来了。
And then you just drive to that solution as fast you can.
然后你就会以最快的速度朝着那个解决方案推进。
And looking back, I recognize that's how I reacted to MIT.
回过头来看，我意识到这正是我当初对 MIT 的反应方式。
So there was no sense that the requirements were
所以当时并没有觉得必修要求是错误的
wrong or any of that.
或诸如此类的想法。
It was just we figured out this is the way to do it.
只是我们搞清楚了这事就该这么做。
And now we are just going to drive to that as
那现在我们只需要
effectively as we can.
尽可能高效地实现它。
And MIT's kind of like that.
MIT 就是这样。
And there are wonderful parts about that.
那里面有很美好的部分。
And there are sort of bad part of that.
也有不太好的部分。
INTERVIEWER: Tell me a bit more about working with
采访者：请再多跟我讲讲你和 Seymour Papert
Seymour Papert.
共事的经历吧。
What was that like?
那是种怎样的体验？
ABELSON: Well, Seymour was, is amazing.
ABELSON：嗯，Seymour 过去是、现在依然是，非常了不起的人。
So I guess people know that tragically he was very
我想大家知道，很不幸他在 Vietnam
severely injured in Vietnam.
受了非常严重的伤。
And his brain was very affected.
他的大脑受到了严重影响。
And he's under rehabilitation now.
他现在正在接受康复治疗。
But Seymour was just absolutely amazing--
但是 Seymour 真的是非常非常了不起——
I mean his childlike sense of wonder at learning.
我是指他那孩子般对学习的好奇。
And what Seymour really is about is learning.
Seymour 真正关注的是学习本身。
So people talk about computing and people talk about math.
人们谈论计算，人们谈论数学。
But with Seymour you are just surrounded by this joy of
但在 Seymour 身边，你会沉浸在
being able to learn.
“能够学习”本身的喜悦当中。
So it's not just math and things.
所以这不仅仅是数学之类的事情。
It's things like, he taught himself when we were there how
比如，我们在的时候，他自学了如何
to work on the bongo board.
玩平衡板（bongo board）。
There's some old AI Lab historic tapes of Seymour
有一些旧的 AI Lab 历史录像带记录了 Seymour
doing the bongo board.
玩平衡板的画面。
And what he loved was to explain to people how you
他热衷向人们解释，你是如何思考
thought about how to balance on the bongo board.
怎样在平衡板上保持平衡的。
He also did it with juggling.
对于抛接球戏法也是同样。
So he sort of had a tremendous--
他做了特别棒的——
teaching people to juggle.
教人如何抛接球。
And his idea was that you could think about that.
他的想法是，你是可以去思考这件事的。
There was a method for thinking about how you juggle.
抛接球戏法是有思考的方法的。
So this thing that looked like a very complicated thing that
所以这件看起来非常复杂、仿佛马戏团演员似的、
a circus person was doing, it almost magic, you could
几乎像魔法一样的事情，实际上是
actually teach it.
可以教授的。
And everything he did was infused with that.
他所做的一切都充满这种精神。
I remember going to visit him in Maine.
我记得有一次去缅因州（Maine）拜访他。
And he wrote this map.
他画了张地图。
And the map, you could tell that he enjoyed writing the
从这张地图上，你可以看出他很享受
directions on this map in a way that people would
用一种人们能理解的方式来写下
understand them.
路线指引。
And of course that went over into math and science.
当然，这也延伸到了数学和科学领域。
So he had exactly the same philosophy that learning about
他秉持着完全相同的哲学，认为学习
math and science isn't magic.
数学和科学并不是魔法。
There's a deliberate, in his way, procedural way of
有一种刻意的，他那种，过程化的方式
thinking about knowledge and about learning.
来思考知识和学习。
Another critical part of that is the notion of debugging.
其中另一个关键部分是调试（debugging）的概念。
So there's this idea that you do something,
有这样一种想法：你在做某件事，
and you make a mistake.
然后犯了一个错误。
And he would always totally emphasize that
他总会全力强调
mistakes are wonderful.
错误是美妙的。
Bugs are just great because that allows you to go back and
Bug（程序错误）非常棒，因为它们让你能
analyze and think about stuff.
回过头去分析和思考。
And all of that influence went not only in my own work in
所有这些影响不仅体现在我自己的教育工作中，
education, but also in the computer science work that
也体现在我与 Gerry Sussman 合作的
Gerry Sussman and I did.
计算机科学工作中。
There's this thing called the procedural
有一种被称为“知识的
explanation of knowledge.
过程性解释”的东西。
One critical thing in teaching people ideas, whether in
在传授理念时，无论是在计算机科学
computer science or anything, is to give them names and to
还是其他领域，一个关键点是给它们命名，然后
use those names and things.
运用这些名称和想法。
And that goes right through all of our work in the Scheme
这一点贯穿在我们在 Scheme 编程语言的全部工作，
programming language and our work in making MIT's first
以及我们创建 MIT 首门
computer science course.
计算机科学课程的工作中。
It goes absolutely, directly back to Seymour.
这绝对能直接追溯到 Seymour。
INTERVIEWER: Were there other key mentors or professors that
采访者：作为研究生，是否还有其他关键的
influenced your development, your intellectual or your
导师或教授影响了您的发展，
professional development as a graduate student.
智识上或者职业上的发展？
ABELSON: Oh well, sure.
ABELSON：噢，那是肯定的。
I mean I wasn't a graduate student in computer science.
我是说，我当时并不是计算机科学系的研究生。
I didn't work for Seymour as a research instructor.
我也不是以研究讲师的身份为 Seymour 工作的。
My research was actually in mathematics under Dennis
我的研究实际上是在数学系，师从 Dennis
Sullivan, who is a very, very famous topologist, who was in
Sullivan，他是一位非常、非常著名的拓扑学家，
the math department at MIT in those days.
当时在 MIT 数学系任教。
And again, he was a little bit different.
同样地，他也有点与众不同。
Dennis was one of these
Dennis 是那种
mathematicians who's just magic.
魔法一样的数学家。
You look at this thing and you say how could this guy
你看他的成果会说，这家伙
possibly have ever thought about this stuff?
怎么可能能想到这种东西的？
And he was just an enormous influence about--
他对我产生了巨大的影响，在——
just sort of this intellectual excellence where the stuff
那种智识上的卓越，想法
springs from nowhere.
无中生有地涌现出来。
And you're just inspired that way.
这样就是会让你深受启发。
INTERVIEWER: So tell me a little bit more about your
采访者：那么，请多讲讲你的职业发展轨迹，
professional path from mathematics to computer
从数学到计算机科学，以及从在 MIT
science and from getting a PhD at MIT to being a
获得博士学位到成为
professor at MIT?
MIT 教授的过程？
ABELSON: Oh, sure.
ABELSON：哦，当然可以。
Well when I got a PhD, I was in the math
嗯，我获得博士学位的时候，是在
department doing topology.
数学系做拓扑学（topology）。
Got an appointment as an instructor.
后来被任命为讲师（instructor）。
But then because I was working in Logo, MIT started something
但后来由于，我在从事 Logo 方面的工作，MIT 在 70 年代中期成立了一个
in the mid-'70s called the Division for Study in Research
名为"科研与教育研究部"（Division for Study in Research and Education，
and Education.
简称 DSRE）的机构。
And it had a couple of key pieces to it.
它有几个关键组成部分。
There were three leaders.
有三位负责人。
One was Ben Snyder, who wrote a very famous book at MIT
一位是 Ben Snyder，他写了一本在 MIT 非常
called The Hidden Curriculum, which is all about how
有名的书，叫做《隐藏的课程》（The Hidden Curriculum），
surviving at MIT is a process of constant triage.
讲的是在 MIT 生存是一个不断取舍的过程。
And students at MIT have to learn that.
MIT 的学生必须了解这一点。
One's Don Schon, who was in the Sloan School, who was very
一位是 Don Schon，他在斯隆学院（Sloan School），
famous for his theories of knowledge or ideas of espoused
以他的知识理论，或说“信奉知识”（espoused knowledge）
knowledge and how you do things.
与实际行动之间关系的思想而闻名。
And the third one which was Seymour doing Logo.
第三个是 Seymour，做 Logo 相关的工作。
So I became part of the Division for Study in Research
于是，我成为了科研与教育研究部
and Education.
的一员。
Got a joint appointment in math and DSRE.
获得了数学系和 DSRE 的联合职务。
And that's where we sort of really started to do Logo work
在那儿，我们开始真正将 Logo 工作作为
as sort of real MIT research kind of stuff.
MIT 的正式研究项目来开展。
But then eventually what happens, MIT decided
但最终发生的情况是，MIT
to close down DSRE.
决定解散 DSRE。
I was sort of too junior then to understand or even be aware
我当时资历太浅，还无法理解甚至没意识到
of the politics behind that.
这背后的政治因素。
But in any case, MIT decided to close it down.
但无论如何，MIT 决定关闭它。
And then I moved into the electrical engineering
然后我进入了电气工程与计算机
computer science department, kind of on the basis of the
科学系，大概是因为 Logo 上的
Logo work and the basis of the fact that I was doing
工作，也因为当时我正在做
distributed computing.
分布式计算。
And that's sort of where I've been sitting.
后来我就一直在那里。
INTERVIEWER: So tell me a bit more about the early Logo work
采访者：那么，请多讲讲早期的 Logo 工作
and your work in distributed computing and how that has
以及你在分布式计算方面的工作，这些是如何
sort of influenced your research path since?
影响你此后的研究道路的？
ABELSON: Well, I don't actually think about Logo and
ABELSON：嗯，我其实不太把 Logo
distributed computing together very much.
和分布式计算放在一起考虑。
INTERVIEWER: Well, we can treat it separately I suppose.
采访者：那，我想我们可以分开来谈。
ABELSON: Other than they kind of both end up being a vision
ABELSON：除了它们最后都成为了对计算的
of computing and being formal about it and things.
某种愿景，而且都很形式化等等。
The Logo work was as I said, magic.
Logo 的工作就像我说的，是魔法。
It is really hard right now to go back.
现在很难回到那个时代了。
We're talking a dozen years before the personal computer.
我们在谈论的是个人计算机出现前的十几年的事情。
What we used to say in Logo is oh my god, if a computer could
我们以前做 Logo 的时候经常说，老天爷，如果
just cost $10,000, that would
一台电脑只要 1 万美元，
revolutionize all of education.
那必将对教育产生彻底变革。
Because what we were doing is these were million machines, a
因为那时我们用的是几百万美元的机器，
million dollars in 1968 dollars.
1968 年的几百万。
They were sitting in the Artificial Intelligence Lab,
它们放在人工智能实验室里，
doing the world's very best, fanciest research an
做着世界上最顶尖、最前沿的人工
artificial intelligence.
智能研究。
And we were hooking them up over phone lines to be used by
而我们却把它们连上电话线，供马萨诸塞州
sixth graders in Lexington, Massachusetts.
列克星敦的六年级学生使用。
And just a totally outrageous thing.
离谱至极的事情。
One my first projects as a graduate student was working
我作为研究生的第一个项目之一，就是做
on a remote display that you could hook up that could sit
一种可以连接的远程显示器，它可以放在
in Lexington and move over a phone line.
列克星敦，通过电话线传输。
And so students could write what was effectively the first
让学生们能编写出事实上的第一个 Logo
Logo turtle and draw designs on this graphics display.
海龟程序，在这个图形显示器上绘制图案。
So that was like my first job as a graduate student,
那是我作为研究生的第一份工作，
implementing that.
实现那个东西。
But it was so off scale.
但它太超出常规了。
Just the very idea that a computer would be something
就是这个“计算机要
that a kid could use.
让孩子能用”的想法。
We take it so it for granted now that it's almost
我们现在对此习以为常，以至于几乎
impossible to put yourself in that mindset.
不可能代入那种思维模式当中。
So most people thought we were crazy, because I mean what a
大多数人觉得我们疯了，因为我是说，
weird thing.
这事太奇怪了。
Why could a computer ever be something that would be
计算机怎么可能与儿童相关，
relevant to a kid, much less programming it or anything?
更别说去给它编程了。
And it was a mixture of what happened in the AI Lab.
这些混在一起，发生在人工智能实验室里。
Every couple of weeks somebody would run in off the street
每隔几周就会有人从街上跑进来，说，
saying, I want to see the robots.
我想看看机器人。
You're making robots.
你们在造机器人。
I want to come see them.
我想要来看看它们。
And AI Lab was just a wonderful mixture of that.
当时的 AI 实验室就是那些的奇妙混合体。
So it was run by Seymour Papert and of course Marvin
它由 Seymour Papert 领导，当然还有
Minsky, who are just two completely brilliant people
Marvin Minsky，他们是两位极其杰出人，
with I think a real sense of faith, in that if you're
我认为他们真正有一种信念，如果你身边
surrounded by a lot of smart people and you give them a lot
围绕着一群聪明人，给他们充分的自由，
of freedom and your job is really to inspire people, it
你的工作实际是去启发他们，这样就能做出
will do great things.
伟大的成就。
And the AI Lab was just infused with that.
人工智能实验室充满了这种理念。
There was just a tremendous sense of community among the
人工智能研究人员之间有种强烈的社区
AI researchers, which was partly true because it was
意识，一部分原因是因为它
pretty small.
相当小。
One of the things that's happened more recently is that
更近一些的时候，它与计算机
merged with the Lab for Computer Science.
科学实验室合并了。
And it doesn't have that same real sense of community and
它不再有之前那种真正的社区意识
flexibility.
和灵活性了。
But the original AI Lab, there have been a much of books
但是原来的人工智能实验室，已经有很多书
written about it, all sorts of things emerged from that.
写过了，各种各样的成功都起源于这些特点。
The other thing that emerged from that, that maybe you want
另一件源于这些特点的事情，也许你之后
to talk about later is Richard Solomon and the whole free
会想谈到，是 Richard Stallman 和整个
software movement, which these days is better known as the
自由软件运动，如今它更为人所知的名称是
Open Source Movement.
开源运动。
But that was a thing--
但那是一件——
I mean in a deep sense it had to do with computer science,
我是说，在深层意义上它与计算机科学有关，
but not obviously.
但并不是很明显。
But it's a whole kind of philosophy that grew out of
它是一整套哲学，源于一种观念，认为
this sense that technology is fundamentally a data community
技术本质上是一个数据社区，本质上是关于一
and fundamentally about a whole bunch of inspired people
群受启发的人彼此分享、在他人工作的
sharing and building on each other's work.
基础上继续构建的事情。
And that of course goes way past software into things like
而这一点远远超出了软件领域，延伸到了像知识共享（Creative Commons）
Creative Commons and lots of the stuff that we see now.
以及我们今天看到的许多事物中。
But it came out of that germ of sharing around
但它起源于技术社区中
a technology community.
分享的萌芽。
INTERVIEWER: Yeah, I want to definitely in a little bit
采访者：是的，我肯定想要探讨下在当下
explore some of these broader ideas in their current form.
形态中的这些更宽泛的理念。
But let's talk a bit about that culture of sharing and of
但让我们先谈谈那时 MIT 里的那种
open networks within MIT at that point.
共享和开放网络文化吧。
I mean I've read that obviously there's a whole sort
我的意思是我读到过，显然当时的安全
of different landscape of security and
和密码体系，或者说它们的缺失，
passwords or lack thereof.
和现在截然不同。
But just describe the environment a bit more at that
但请再多描述下当时的环境，以及
time and how obviously it had effects later.
它是如何显而易见地对后来产生影响的。
ABELSON: Well remember for thinking
ABELSON：嗯，要知道站在
about now, the internet--
现在的角度，互联网——
it wasn't an internet then-- the ARPANET was a small place.
那时还称不上互联网——ARPANET 是一个很小的地方。
And it really was a very small, very,
它真的是一个非常小，非常、
very homogeneous place.
非常同质化的地方。
I like to tell people I've had my email address since I kind
我常常跟人说，自从我几乎认识所有可以互发
of knew all of the people that I could have send email to.
邮件的人起，我就一直使用这个电子邮件地址。
I mean it's been written a lot that people who originally
我是说有很多记录，最初设计
designed the internet said they just sort of did not
互联网的人们说，他们设计互联网
design the internet architecture to think that
架构时根本没有考虑过那里
there would be bad guys out there.
会有坏人。
Because they knew all the people.
因为他们认识所有的人。
All the people were like them.
所有的人都和他们一样。
And that reflected over in passwords.
这一点也体现在了密码上。
I remember there was one sort of dark day when the people
我记得有那么一个“黑暗的日子”，ARPA 的人说，
from ARPA said, you need to put passwords on your accounts
你们必须给账户加上密码，
because they're on the network.
因为它们连网了。
And for security, you need to do that.
安全起见，你们必须这样做。
And a whole bunch of us were just convinced this was a
我们一大群人就坚信这是一个
horrible idea.
糟糕透顶的主意。
I mean what a terrible idea that you'd have to put a
我是说，这想法也太糟糕了，
password in an account and people could get into it.
你得在账户上设置密码，才能登录帐号。
I remember Richard Stallman reacted to this by making his
我记得 Richard Stallman 的反应是把他的密码设为 RMS，
password RMS, which was initials.
也就是他名字的首字母缩写。
So just jumping ahead a little bit, if you move about 10, 12
所以稍微快进一点，大约 10 到 12 年后，
years later, my daughter, when she was about oh 14,
我的女儿，大约 14 岁时，向我介绍了
introduced me to what became known as MUDS or multiplayer
一种后来被称为 MUDS 或者互联网多人在线
games on the internet.
游戏的东西。
I had no idea this thing existed.
我之前完全不知道这种东西的存在。
And I was introduced to this by my, what she then, she
介绍我看这个的是我的，她当时大概
probably was maybe about 13.
13 岁左右。
And I come home and she says daddy, do you know there's
我回到家，她说爸爸，你知道吗，
this thing on the computer that all kids in the whole
电脑上有个东西，全世界的孩子
world can use?
都能用？
And I say, gosh no.
我说，老天，不知道。
And she says, I'll show you.
她说，我给你看看。
And she says you have to dial this phone number.
然后她说，你得拨这个电话号码。
So she starts dialing this phone number.
然后她开始拨打这个电话号码。
And I say, oh my god, that's my lab at MIT.
我说，老天爷，那是我在 MIT 的实验室。
That's the terminus server to my lab at MIT.
那是连到 MIT 我的实验室的终端服务器。
And she says yeah, you have this thing.
她说，是啊，你们有这个玩意。
And it types out this funny star or something.
它会打印出奇怪的星号和其他东西。
And now I'm supposed to type R-M-S. And I say, oh my god,
现在我应该按 R-M-S。我说，老天爷，
you're typing Stallman's password to
你在输入 Stallman 的密码
get into the system.
来登入系统。
And she goes from that and starts up playing this game.
然后她就继续下去，开始玩这个游戏。
And it was great.
那感觉太棒了。
She had no idea that this was MIT.
她完全不知道这是 MIT。
She had no idea what RMS meant.
她也不知道 RMS 代表什么。
But there were kids all over the world who were doing this.
但是全世界的孩子们都在这么干。
And that's a little bit of the spirit of sharing and openness
这体现了一点点，那种共享和开放的精神，
and delight that comes from that.
以及随之而来的喜悦。
That's just really hard to do now.
现在真的很难再做到了。
Because again, the network is a much less homogeneous place
因为同样，网络已经远远不再是像以前那样同质化
than it used to be.
的地方了。
But that's a little bit of what that AI Lab kind of
但它就是一件小事，关于我记忆中
spirit I remember, just to give you another little
人工智能实验室的精神，再给你讲一个
anecdote about that, that's fun.
小轶事，挺有意思的。
I don't know if you've interviewed Joel Moses?
我不知道你采访过 Joel Moses 吗？
INTERVIEWER: Not personally, but yeah.
采访者：我个人没有，但是我们采访过。
ABELSON: So Joel Moses at that time was the head of the
ABELSON：Joel Moses 当时是符号数学
symbolic mathematics project.
项目的负责人。
That's really the great thing that he did, before becoming
那真的是他的伟大成就，在他成为教务长之前，
provost, sort of inventing symbolic mathematics.
可以说是创造了符号数学。
And there was a whole big dispute between him and one of
当时他和一位去了 Berkeley 的前学生
his ex-students who had gone to Berkeley.
之间有过一段激烈的争论。
And there was a dispute about who should get access to this
争论的内容是谁能获得这个 Maxima 软件程序的
Maxima program and should it be licensed and not licensed.
访问权，以及该不该给它加上授权许可。
And there was a fairly heated email exchange that went
Joel 和 Rich Fateman 之间有一场相当
between Joel and Rich Fateman.
激烈的电子邮件交流。
And of course, everyone could read everybody else's
那时理所当然地，每个人可以读到所有其他人的
email at that time.
电子邮件。
And they decided that people in the lab were wasting so
后来他们决定，实验室的人浪费了太多时间看
much time reading Joel's email that they simply translated
Joel 的邮件，干脆直接把 Joel 所有的
all of Joel's email to message of the day.
邮件都转换成了每日消息。
So you all saw it when you logged on.
这样你们所有人一登录系统立马就能看到它。
And that's a little bit again, the sense of playfulness and
这再次体现了一点点，那种玩心和开放的感觉，
openness and we're all part of this big community and the
我们都是这个大社区的一部分，计算机系统是
computer system is a way of empowering that.
让它成真的一种方式。
And I do believe that had a whole lot to do especially
我相信所有这些尤其与分时系统（time sharing）的
with the development of time sharing.
发展有很大关系。
In a sense sort of Bob Fano and Corby Corbato, when they
某种意义上说 Bob Fano 和 Corby Corbato，
started the time sharing project, it was sort of about
当他们一开始做分时系统项目时，
technology.
基本是关注于技术。
But pretty soon they realized really what they'd done is
但很快他们意识到，他们实质上是创造了
create a new kind of community.
一种新型社区。
And to their credit they recognized that very, very
值得称赞的是，他们很早就认识到了这一点，
early and pushed the sense of gee, there's
并推动了这种观念，哎，
a thing like community.
有一种东西叫做社区。
There is an information community.
有一种信息社区。
MIT was one the first places that really did that in a
MIT 是最早真正有意识地做到
conscious way.
这一点的地方之一。
And again, this all comes out of the same kind
同样，这一切都源于同样的
of culture of openness.
开放文化。
INTERVIEWER: Yeah, we'll return to the whole question
采访者：是的，我们稍后会回到开放网络、
of open networks, Open Source a bit later.
开源的整个问题。
I want to turn a little bit in a different direction and ask
我想稍微换个方向，问问你在计算机科学教学
a bit about your interest and professional development of
方面的兴趣和职业发展经历，关于 6.001
teaching computer science, of the development of 6.001 and
课程的发展，还有与 Gerald Sussman 的
also your work with Gerald Sussman and the book.
合作以及那本书的工作。
And maybe, I don't know if this is a productive way of
或许，我不确定这是否是个有效的
leading into it, but it's a question I'm
切入点，但这是一个我非常好奇
really curious about.
的问题。
You mentioned very early on that when you were growing up,
你刚才最早提到过，在成长的过程中，
you were bad at arithmetic, but found out later that you
你并不擅长算术，但后来发现自己其实
were good at math.
很擅长数学。
And I think that's very fascinating.
我觉得这非常耐人寻味。
How does one think about math in a way that makes that true?
要以何种方式来看待数学，才能让这件事成立的呢？
I mean they're impossible that could be bad at arithmetic,
我是说，似乎不可能一个人算术很差
but good at math.
但数学很好。
ABELSON: I don't know.
ABELSON：我不知道。
I don't view arithmetic as having very much to do with
事实上，我并不认为算术和数学
math in fact.
有多大关系。
And I think there are a lot of people in
而且我认为很多人都有
kind of the same boat.
类似的看法。
Again, there's theories that people who go into these
如前面说的，有一些理论认为，投身于这些
developmental fields are doing it in some sense to make up
发展领域的人，在某种程度上是为了弥补自己的
for their own deficits, to try them.
不足，去尝试挑战它们。
So I sort of view it kind of that way.
所以我多少是以这种方式来看待的。
But again, I've always been interested in puzzling out
但同样如前面说的，我一直都对把事情琢磨透、
things and explaining things.
把事情讲清楚感兴趣。
I wasn't very much interested in teaching until I, gosh,
我曾经对教学并不是很感兴趣，直到我，老天，
until I got to MIT in fact.
直到我来到了 MIT，实际上。
But it was mostly explaining things to myself.
但那更多是把事情解释给我自己听。
Being in a couple of very good summer high school programs,
我参加过几个非常好的高中暑期项目，一个在
one at University of Notre Dame, which has since moved to
圣母大学（University of Notre Dame），后来搬到了俄亥俄州，
Ohio State, which had a long, long, long track record of
它在激励人们学习数学方面有着很长，很长，
inspiring people in mathematics.
很长的历史。
One at Cornell, in physics.
另一个在康奈尔大学，是关于物理的。
So that's another kind of educational link that I was
所以那是我接触到的另一类与教育有关的
exposed to.
连接。
And later, my colleague Andy diSessa and I ran that kind of
后来，我和我的同事 Andy diSessa
summer high school program at MIT around computer science
在 MIT 举办过那种高中暑期项目，围绕计算机科学、
and Logo and teaching things.
Logo 以及教学来展开。
So I've been interested in education kind of from that
所以从那个角度来看，我一直都对教育
perspective.
很感兴趣。
I've also played around with computers in education.
我也尝试过将计算机应用于教育。
One of the things I did in the math department was I was
我在数学系做过的一件事是教
teaching linear algebra.
线性代数的时候。
And I think just for the heck of it, I did what must have
我记得只是为了好玩，我设计了应该是
been one of the very first MIT computer exercises where
MIT 最早的计算机练习之一，让学生们
students used the Multics computer system in those days
使用当时的 Multics 计算机系统，
to do some exercise at the end of the day about matrices.
在一天结束时做一些关于矩阵的练习。
Now I didn't know what I was doing.
当时我并不知道自己在做什么。
And it wasn't particularly good and wasn't particularly
它并不是特别出色，也不是
successful.
特别成功。
But it was kind of foray into saying, gosh these MIT
但那是一次初步的尝试说，老天，这些
computers might actually get used in courses.
MIT 的计算机或许真的能用在课程中。
Not much of that happened for a long time after that though.
不过在那之后很长一段时间里，没有太多类似的事情。
INTERVIEWER: Thinking about teaching computer science
采访者：具体到计算机科学的教学，
specifically, can you talk a bit about the Structure and
能谈谈《计算机程序的构造和解释》
Interpretation of Computer Programs and what that grew
这本书，它的来源，以及你们
out of and what the sort of fundamental concepts are
教学方法背后的
behind your approach?
基本概念吗？
ABELSON: So Gerry Sussman and I, I think were really
ABELSON：所以 Gerry Sussman 和我，
privileged in that we wrote a book that really was able to
我觉得我们真的很荣幸能写这样一本书，它充分
draw on that whole of a 20-year history of how MIT and
借鉴了整整 20 年来 MIT 以及整个
that whole AI culture thought about computing.
人工智能文化圈对“计算”的思考。
And it goes directly back to again Seymour Papert and
再一次，这又能直接追溯到 Seymour Papert
Marvin Minsky.
和 Marvin Minsky。
And it really has to do with--
它的核心是——
what's the phrase we used-- a computer program is a way of
我们怎么说的来着——计算机程序是
expressing ideas and communicating ideas, and only
表达想法和交流想法的手段，
incidentally about getting a machine to do stuff.
让机器做事只是附带的结果。
That is straight out of--
这直接源于——
I don't think Seymour used those words, but that's
Seymour 应该没有说过这句话，但这
straight out of the Logo philosophy of
直接源于 Logo 的哲学：我们是在
we're teaching you--
教你——
like I talked about juggling before.
正如刚才谈到的抛接球一样。
This really is, what's the procedure for how you juggle?
本质上是，抛接球到底是怎样的过程？
And critical in being able to do that is having the right
要能教会它，至关重要的是拥有一套
set of words and having the right descriptive framework
恰当的词汇和恰当的描述框架，来
for saying things like that.
表达这类事情。
And so the key idea in Structure and Interpretation
所以《结构与解释》中的关键思想，
is what we ended up calling the linguistic approach to
我们最终称之为“语言学方法”的程序设计，
programming design, which says if I would like to do some
意思是说如果我想做一些非常复杂的
very complicated thing, one of the critical tasks is picking
事情，关键任务之一是选择恰当的描述框架
the right descriptive framework for saying that.
来表达它。
So there is a complete blend.
这是对之前那些想法的完全融合。
I think somewhere in that book we wrote that when you make a
我记得在书中某处我们写道，当你
complicated program, you're actually designing a special
编写一个复杂的程序时，你实际上在设计
purpose computer language to solve a problem.
一个专门的程序语言来解决问题。
And it comes through in lots and lots of ways.
这点体现在很多很多方面。
So it goes back I think to the AI culture, which has the
我觉得它起源于人工智能文化，它有
property that you don't quite know what problem you're
一个特点是你不太清楚你要解决
solving because these things are really complicated.
什么问题，因为它们非常复杂。
It's not as if someone says compute the total payment on
它不像有人让你计算出这笔抵押贷款的
this mortgage where you know exactly what
总还款额，你很清楚知道接下来
you're going to do.
要做什么。
Rather it says, you want to be mucking around in this area to
相反，它是要你在这个领域摸索，来解决
solve this problem and lots and lots and lots and lots of
这个问题，以及很多、很多、很多、很多
similar problems.
类似的问题。
And that permeates both the design of the book and the
这种理念既贯穿于本书的设计中，
actual programming technology that people use.
也贯穿于人们实际使用的编程技术里。
So the style of programming languages that go back to LISP
因此起源自 LISP 的编程语言风格是
is really sort of muddier.
相当“浑浊”的。
It's not a very precise kind of thing.
它并不是种非常精确的东西。
You make ways of programming things where you're solving
你摸索出的编程方式，解决的
not just one problem but a whole family
不仅仅是一个问题，而是
of problems in that.
一整类问题。
And again, it goes back to very, very technical things,
这又再次源于一些非常、非常技术性的东西，
like LISP is a very good language for creating other
比如 LISP 这门语言非常适合用来创建其他
computer languages.
计算机语言。
Because when you're programming in LISP, you
因为当你用 LISP 编程时，你实际上
actually have the mentality of gosh, I'm actually creating
有一种心态，老天，我实际上是在创建某种
some special purpose language to solve not just one problem,
专用语言，不仅是为了解决一个问题，而是为了
but lots of them.
解决很多问题。
And that's the critical idea in Structure and
而这正是《构造与解释》中的
Interpretation.
核心思想。
I mean we can't take credit for that.
我想说，这不是我们自己的发明。
We were just blessed that there was a whole tradition of
我们只是很幸运，在 MIT 和其他
20 years of really deep thinking at MIT and a couple
几个类似的地方有整整 20 年的
of other similar places.
深度思考的传承。
And we sort of got to be the people who got to
而我们只是恰好成为了把那些思考
put that in the book.
写进书里的人。
And it's had enormous influence, but it's not
这本书产生了巨大的影响，但那并不是因为
because of us, it's because the tremendous power of those
我们个人，而是因为那些思想本身以及孕育出
ideas and the communities that they came from.
它们的那些社区所拥有的强大力量。
INTERVIEWER: So moving beyond those communities that the
采访者：那么，等走出孕育出这本书以及
book and that thought process came out of, did you encounter
那种思考方式的社群之后，你们有没有
resistance, maybe that's not the right word, maybe
遇到过阻力——也许这个词不太准确，
misunderstanding--
或许该说是误解——
people who were focused on the syntax?
从关注点在语法上的人那里？
ABELSON: So we published this with MIT Press.
ABELSON：我们跟 MIT 出版社出版这本书后。
And MIT Press sent it out for reviews.
MIT 出版社把它送出去做评审。
And the first review came back.
回来的第一份评审意见。
And I'll never forget.
我永远都不会忘记。
It said, quote, the question is, is in MIT Press publishing
它写到，原话：“问题在是，MIT 出版社出版
this book going to advance or set back computer science?
这本书，是会推动还是会阻碍计算机科学的发展？”
So there was a lot of resistance to this because
所以当时对此有很多阻力，因为它
it's just very different.
实在太不一样了。
And there's a lot of people who really don't believe in
有很多人真的不认同
that approach, who really do think it's the wrong thing.
这种方法，真心认为这样不对。
Because again, it's this notion of you don't actually
因为刚才讲的，它的理念是不要把关注点
focus on solving this problem very, very, very precisely.
放在非常、非常、非常精确地解决某个问题。
There's a whole movement in computer science, a
计算机科学界有一整派运动，
tremendously respectable one, and it says a program is like
备受尊敬，它认为一段程序就像
the proof of a mathematical theorem.
一段对数学定理的证明。
And there are people who do prove things about programs.
也确实有人在做关于程序的证明。
That in some sense is the mainstream almost. Whereas
从某种意义上说，那几乎就是主流思想。而
we're saying well, a program is sort of like a language.
我们却说，嗯，一段程序像是一门语言。
Like you can say lots of things.
好比你可以说很多事情。
And I don't imagine I'm going to prove everything
我不认为我要证明
I'm going to say.
我说的每件事。
It's just that the great thing is I get to see all these
关键是，最棒的事情在于我能看到所有
different things.
这些不同的事物。
So we've had a lot of influence, but I wouldn't even
所以我们产生了很大的影响，但我肯定
say that we're mainstream, even now.
不会说我们是主流，哪怕是现在。
INTERVIEWER: From my limited experience when I think back
采访者：从我有限的经验看，回忆起
to my computer programming classes, it was more like the
我上计算机编程课程时，它更像是
mathematical theorem approach.
那种数学定理的方法。
Yeah.
是的。
ABELSON: Exactly right.
ABELSON：完全正确。
It is.
确实如此。
INTERVIEWER: So talk about 6.001 and the development of
采访者：那么我们来谈谈 6.001 和
that class, which is obviously closely related
它的发展，这显然与这本书密切
to the book, right?
相关，对吧？
ABELSON: Gosh.
ABELSON：老天爷。
So the other person who really deserves enormous credit for
还有一位对这一切功不可没的人，
this is Bob Fano.
他是 Bob Fano。
There was a tradition of, what was the first MIT computer
当时有一个传统：MIT 第一门计算机科学
science course?
课程是什么？
There was one taught by Mike Dertouzos and
有一门课是 Mike Dertouzos 和
Steve Ward for awhile.
Steve Ward 教的。
But when I got involved with this, Bob Fano
但等我参与进来的时候，是 Bob Fano
was teaching this.
在教这门课。
It was called 6.035.
叫 6.035。
And what was it called?
它叫什么名字来着？
I think it might have been called Structure and
我记得可能叫《计算机语言的构造和解释》
Interpretation of Computer Languages.
（Structure and Interpretation of Computer Languages）。
And it was very focused on, here's this kind of language.
它非常专注于，对这样一种语言的介绍。
The language then was ALGOL people used.
那时教的语言是当时用的多的 ALGOL。
And then it did a little bit of LISP.
然后也稍微讲了一点 LISP。
And it was kind of an okay course.
算是门还不错的课程。
Mostly famous because it was the first course.
它出名主要是因为它是第一门课程。
But Fano did say the key thing.
但 Fano 确实说了关键的东西。
So I talked about what you're doing is making a language and
我刚才说到了，编程本质是创造一门语言，
how you make languages to make languages.
以及你如何通过创造语言来创造语言。
The technical term for that is an interpreter.
对应的术语叫作解释器（interpreter）。
So an interpreter is something that effectively takes the
解释器本质是，接收对一门语言的
description of a language and lets the computer effectively
描述，然后让计算机等于是用那门
speak that language.
语言“说话”。
And Fano was very--
而 Fano 非常——
I mean he would say this in his lectures.
我的意思是，他会在课堂上这么说。
I don't think any of the students got it.
我觉得当时没有学生真的听懂了。
I didn't get it until like the third time through, where he
我自己反复听了三遍课才明白，
sort of said the really, really key thing is that you
他大概是说，最最关键的事情
build up complexity by constructing an interpreter.
在于通过构建一个解释器来堆砌复杂度。
And again, that's the core idea of 6.001, said in a
像刚才说的，这是 6.001 的核心思想，
slightly different way.
只是说法略有不同。
So he had an enormous, enormous influence on us, but
所以他对我们产生了极其、极其重大的影响，而且
also more directly.
还有另一个更加直接的影响。
So about this time, there was a tradition in the electrical
有一次，电气工程与计算机科学系里
engineering computer science department of when the
有一个传统：系里在 50 年代末
department did the transition from kind of power engineering
从电力工程转向信号工程的时候，
to signals engineering in the late '50s, led by people like
在 Ernie Guillemin 以及其他 MIT
Ernie Guillemin and those sort legends at MIT, there was a
那些传奇人物的带领下， 催生了
very, very influential series of textbooks that came out, I
一系列非常、非常有影响力的教材，
think in the late '50s, early '60s, that almost sort of set
我想是在 50 年代末、60 年代初，
the academic marker for the field of electrical
它们几乎为电气工程领域
engineering.
树立了学术标杆。
So when we were there in the in the late '70s and very
所以当我们在 70 年代末、80 年代初
beginning of the '80s, Joel Moses and Gerry Wilson wanted
在那里时，Joel Moses 和 Gerry Wilson 想要
to do that again.
再来一次。
So there was this notion that there would be a series of new
所以当时有一种想法，系里要
courses and new books that the department would put out.
推出一系列新的课程和新的书籍。
And then what was going to be the computing one?
那么，讲计算的那本会是哪本呢？
So Fano basically backed that Gerry and I would do the
Fano 就支持由 Gerry 和我来编写
computing one and do the computing course.
关于计算的书、教关于计算的课。
And again, there was a lot of a lot of controversy there
刚才也说了，这里有很多、很多争议，
because people didn't believe it.
因为人们不相信它。
Fano was sort of the power in the department who really made
Fano 某种程度上是系里的权威中，真正
it possible for us to do that.
让我们能做成这件事情的人。
Gerry and I sort of happened into this.
Gerry 和我只是误打误撞。
So we were sort of lucky.
我们可以说是走运了。
And just very, very fortunate that there were some smart
而且非常、非常幸运，有那些
people backing us.
聪明的人支持我们。
INTERVIEWER: How has introductory curriculum in ECS
采访者：从那时起，ECS（电气工程与计算机科学系）的
changed since that time?
入门课程发生了怎样的变化？
I mean clearly it's--
我是说，很明显它——
ABELSON: Oh, it's changed a lot.
ABELSON：哦，变化很大。
INTERVIEWER: Yeah.
采访者：是啊。
ABELSON: I don't know.
ABELSON：我也说不太清楚。
People keep using the phrase bittersweet.
人们一直用“苦乐参半”这个词来形容。
It's changed in style.
它的风格改变了。
So what happened in the department is the department
所以，系里发生的事情是，
kind of decided that the way students get introduced into
系里某种程度上决定，学生进入这个系的
the department should become more horizontal and less
引介方式应该变得更“横向”，而不是
vertical, by which I mean when you go into the department
那么“纵向”，我的意思是，在
before the new curriculum, there were a bunch of very
新课程体系之前你进到系里的时候，
intellectually deep courses.
会有一系列极具智力深度的课程。
So 6.001 really is a deep course in software
比如 6.001 实际上是一门在软件工程方面
engineering.
非常深入的课程。
And then the idea was well, you shouldn't actually do that
之后的想法是，其实不应该这样做，
because if students want to think about what they want to
因为如果学生要思考自己主修
major in, they ought to get an experience
什么专业，他们应该有
that's a lot more broad.
更加广泛的体验。
So they should learn not only about software, but something
所以他们不仅应该学习软件，还应该
about circuits and something about signal
学一点电路、学一点
processing and all that.
信号处理，等等这些。
So 6.001 sort of didn't fit into that world.
所以 6.001 有点不适合那个体系。
I sort was on the committee.
我算是委员会的一员。
I had this funny feeling.
我有一种奇怪的感觉。
I sort of loved the course.
我挺喜欢这门课程。
But I also had this feeling that the
但我也有种感觉，
course needed to change.
这门课需要改变。
And both Gerry and I felt that as long as we were part of it,
而且 Gerry 和我都觉得，只要我们还参与其中，
it wasn't going to change.
它就不会改变。
And in fact we consciously got out of it.
事实上我们刻意地从中退出了。
We had an official, what you call passing of the baton
我们在其中一堂课上举行了一个正式的，所谓的
ceremony in one of the lectures where Bob Fano was
交接仪式，Bob Fano 也在场，作为
there as the originator of this, who let us do 6.001.
这门课的发起人，是他让我们开设了 6.001。
And then Eric Grimson and Duane Boning were there.
然后 Eric Grimson 和 Duane Boning 也在场。
They were going to take it over.
他们将接手这门课。
And we kind of officially passed the baton.
我们算是正式进行了交接。
And we said we now did this in front
然后我们说，我们现在是
of 350 student witnesses.
在 350 名学生的见证之下。
We are never going to teach this course again.
我们永远不会再教这门课了。
The department can't ask us.
系里不能要求我们教。
But then what happened is even after we got out of it, the
结果后来，即使在我们退出之后，这门
course didn't change as much.
课程也没有太大变化。
And we can flatter ourselves and say well, the ideas were
我们可以自吹自擂说，嗯，因为那些理念
just really great.
实在很棒。
But sometimes you just need a kick in the pants to go
但是有时候你就是得屁股上来一脚，
someplace else.
才能去到别的地方。
So this new department curriculum structure turned
所以系里这个新的课程体系成了
out to be the kick in the pants.
屁股上来的那一脚。
And so I was part of the group, along with Leslie
我成了新课程组的一员，和 Leslie Kaelbling，
Kaelbling and Jacob White and Tomas Lozano-Perez, who sort
Jacob White 还有 Tomas Lozano-Perez
of designed sort of the new course, which consciously was
一起，基本上是他们设计了新课程，刻意不再围绕
not about 6.001.
6.001 展开。
But a lot of the biggest themes of 6.001 about
但 6.001 中许多最重要的主题，
extraction and modularity and the way you express things,
关于抽象、模块化，以及如何表达，
they carry over into the new course.
延续到了新课程中。
But the new course is also doing robotics.
但新课程还涉及机器人学。
And it's thinking that signal processing.
还有信号处理的思想。
And there's even some stuff about circuits.
甚至还有一些关于电路的内容。
So it's not a deep course in that sense.
所以从这个意义上说，它不是一门深入的课程。
And there's a lot of people who have come through MIT--
有很多 MIT 毕业的人——
I don't want to take credit for 6.001 and that, but I want
我不想把 6.001 和下面的话归功于己，
to say it was a very deep experience in how
但我想说，它是关于如何思考软件
you think of software--
的一个非常深入的体验——
who criticized what we did.
他们曾经批评过我们的做法。
And they say they really miss it.
后来说他们真的很怀念那门课。
They talk about their own intellectual development as
他们提到他们作为程序员，个人的
programmers.
智识发展。
It was just profoundly influenced by
深刻地影响了他们，
that kind of very--
那种非常——
we would sit in that class and talk about
我们有时会坐在那门课上，
the philosophy sometimes.
谈论哲学。
The new course does not do that in the same way.
新课程里不再有这样的方式了。
On the other hand, you have to sort of ask what's the
另一方面，你必须得问，你究竟在
population you're serving?
服务怎样的学生群体？
And the fact that you talk to the minority of students who
事实是，如果你和少数那些真的、真的接受了
really, really glommed on to our way of thinking and they
我们思维方式的学生交谈，他们会说，
say, gee, we really wish MIT were still doing that.
哎呀，我们真的希望 MIT 还那样教课。
I don't know what the right way of serving the most
我不知道服务大多数学生的正确方式
students are.
是什么。
But in any case we're just doing something rather
但无论如何，我们现在做的事情，
different in motivation now.
出发点已经大不相同。
INTERVIEWER: So it's broader, but less deep.
采访者：所以它涉猎更广，但不那么深入。
ABELSON: And very consciously less deep.
ABELSON：并且非常有意地不那么深入。
INTERVIEWER: Right.
采访者：对。
What are MIT students like?
MIT 的学生是什么样的？
I mean how do they respond to the deep dive on the one hand
我的意思是，他们对一边是这种深入的课程，
or the sort of broad fire hose on the other of having to deal
另一边是必须应付各种不同内容的
with all of these different things?
“大消防水枪”式的教学，有什么反应？
ABELSON: I think you can't generalize.
ABELSON：我认为你不能一概而论。
Right.
对。
There are certainly some, I'm going to say kind of the
确实有一些，我会说是那种
mathematical ones.
偏数学型的学生。
So even though it's not mathematics, that kind of deep
虽然不是数学，但那种深入的课程也
thing is a math kind of experience.
是一种数学式的体验。
And they really would rather have something that's more
他们真的宁愿要更像原来的
like the original 6.001.
6.001 的课程。
But then there are a whole bunch of others
但还有一大批其他学生，
who just want to--
他们只想——
I just want to understand the breath of this field I'm
我只想了解我要进入的这个
getting into.
领域的广度。
I don't want to just because I'm going to major in
我不想仅仅因为我要主修电气工程，
electrical engineering, have to take a whole semester of
就非得学上一整学期这些其他的
this other stuff, most of which is kind of
东西，其中大部分
irrelevant to me.
对我来说都无关紧要。
So again, I don't have a good sense of how the students are
所以刚才也说了，我对现在学生们的感受
feeling about the population it's serving.
和这个课程的受众不是特别有把握。
Because we did this other thing at the same time, which
因为我们同时还做了另一件事，
as far as students I think has a much bigger impact.
我认为就学生而言，影响要大得多。
So there's a whole other stream which we haven't talked
在 MIT 还有另一条我们还没谈到的脉络：
about at MIT and active learning, which comes from the
主动学习（active learning），源于我和
stuff I've been doing with the
教育技术委员会（Educational Technology Council）
Educational Technology Council.
一直在做的事情。
But we made a radical, radical change in the style of the
但我们对课程风格做了一个彻头彻尾的
course, which was removing most of the lectures.
改变，就是去掉了大部分讲座。
So in the new course, the main thing you do with your time is
所以在新课程中，你主要的时间都花在
you work on a project.
做一个项目上。
And there's a big giant open lab.
有个巨大的开放实验室。
And the entire teaching staff of the course is present in
课程的全体教学人员都在这个
this open lab.
开放实验室里。
And there's kind of a pyramidal structure where
那里有一种金字塔结构，
there are undergraduate laboratory assistants, and
先是本科生实验室助理，
each group of them is kind of supervised by a graduate
他们分组后由研究生助教监督，
student TA, and each group of graduate student TA's are
研究生助教再分组后再由
supervised by the actual course faculty.
真正的课程教师监督。
And we're all sort of mixing it up in the course and
我们所有人都在课程中混合在一起，
sitting there talking to individual students.
坐在那里与单个学生交谈。
So rather than sitting in lecture, it's this very kind
所以，与坐在那里听讲座相反，它是一种
of open, interactive project-based thing.
非常开放、互动的、基于项目的学习方式。
And that's such an enormous change in style, that when you
这种风格上的改变是如此巨大，以至于决定
kind of ask the students well, do you like it more, how you
课程内容的主要因素是，我们去问学生，
react to it more, that's got to dominate what we were doing
嗯，你们更喜欢它吗，怎么能
in terms of content.
让你更有反应呢？
INTERVIEWER: Yeah.
采访者：是啊。
I want to actually ask a whole set of questions on
我其实想就教育技术和
educational technology and the developments you've been
你所参与推动的进展提出
involved in.
一整套问题。
Before turning to that, at the risk of asking to generalize
在转向那个话题之前，虽然又可能要冒昧地引出
again about MIT students, is there any way of talking about
对 MIT 学生的一概而论，但能否谈谈在你的
how or whether MIT students have changed over the course
职业生涯中，MIT 学生是如何，
of your career?
或者是否发生了变化？
ABELSON: Oh, god.
ABELSON: 哦，老天爷。
You get the feeling that about every three years there's a
会有种感觉，大约每三年就会出现
new generation.
新一代学生。
So the main way MIT students have changed I think is that
我认为 MIT 学生最主要的变化是他们
they're more docile, as much as I hate to say.
更温顺了，尽管我很不想这么说。
Marilee Jones, who was admissions director, actually
当时的招生主任 Marilee Jones，实际上
thought about this a lot.
对此思考了很多。
Remember in the '60s, MIT took half of its applicants.
还记得在 60 年代，MIT 会录取一半的申请者。
And now it takes what, 10 percent, under 10 percent?
而现在录取多少，10%，不到 10%？
And the students who end up getting into MIT are coming
最终能进入 MIT 的学生来自
from a way more competitive environment.
一个竞争激烈得多的环境。
And in general, and in tremendous exceptions, they
总体而言，除了极少数例外，他们
have been successful by kind of listening to their parents
之所以成功，某种程度上是因为他们
and listening to adults.
听父母的话，听成年人的话。
And that's led to a tendency that students I think have too
我认为这导致了一种倾向，学生对
much respect for what adults or like faculty or something
成年人或者教职人员之类的人所说的话
are saying.
过于尊重。
So there's really a sense of just kind of well they sort of
于是就形成了一种意识：那些人似乎
know better and they have good things.
更懂，那些人有好的想法。
And they go along it.
他们就顺着来。
And there's not as much a sense of really challenging
真正去挑战体制的想法
the system.
没有那么强了。
Now I don't know whether that's a generational thing or
我不知道这是一整代人的事情，
whether it's this particular kind of influence at the top
还是像 MIT 这样的顶尖学校所
schools like MIT.
特有的影响。
When's the last time you saw students take over
你最后一次看到学生占领 MIT 的
a building at MIT?
大楼是什么时候？
Like I said, when I showed up at MIT when I saw that happen,
就像刚才说的，我刚到 MIT 时看到那种
I said what incredibly an healthy thing to happen.
情况时，我说那是多么健康的事情啊。
And now we get upset if students
而现在，如果学生黑进了电梯，
crack into an elevator.
我们都会感到不安。
So there's really this sense of the students becoming--
所以真的有一种感觉，学生变得--
I mean docile may be not quite-- the wrong word--
我是说，“温顺”可能不太--不恰当--
but sort of too much respect for what the
但有点过于尊重
Institution is doing.
学校的做法了。
And I sort of wish that would change.
我多少希望这种情况能改变。
So that's sort of the big change that I see.
这基本就是我看到的重大变化。
INTERVIEWER: What price do we pay if the students are more
采访者：如果学生更循规蹈矩、按部就班，
sort of quick to fall in line or to do what's expected,
而不是去突破边界，我们会
rather than to push boundaries, I mean if any?
付出什么代价，如果有的话？
ABELSON: I think its brilliance, its creativity,
ABELSON:我认为代价是才华、
its achievement.
创造力和成就。
When you think about any place or MIT, you sort of think in
当你去思考一个地方时，包括 MIT，你多少会用
terms of the characters.
那里的“人物”去衡量。
Who are the characters around this place who give it
那个地方有哪些人物，给它增添了
tremendous flavor?
浓郁的风味？
Maybe they're not the smartest people or doing
也许他们并不是最聪明的人，也没有
the greatest things.
在做最伟大的事情。
But they add spice to it.
但他们为它增添了味道。
And you have to make room and just really venerate those
我们得给这种人留出空间，真的
kind of people.
崇敬那种人。
And the more we worry about those people are going to be
而我们越是担心这些人会做出
doing something destructive or they'll be wasting time or
破坏性的事情，或者浪费时间，
they'll be wasting resources or something, the more you
或者浪费资源之类的，我们就
lose that kind of spice.
越会失去那种味道。
And I sort of hope MIT never loses that, although there's
我希望 MIT 永远不要失去它，
just a lot of I don't quite want to say regimentation, but
尽管现在有很多的，我不太想说是
it's just I'd say a little lack of
教条，但我会说是
tolerance for the oddballs.
有点缺少对怪才的容忍。
And we have to just treasure the oddballs more.
我们必须更加珍惜那些怪才。
INTERVIEWER: So turning to educational technology, you've
采访者：那么转到教育技术这个话题，
been deeply involved in any number of initiatives and
自从你来到 MIT 之后就一直
deployment of programs since you've been at MIT.
深度参与了许多项目的倡议和实施。
ABELSON: Since 1969.
ABELSON: 从 1969 年开始。
INTERVIEWER: Yes.
采访者：是的。
Tell me first of all where does that interest come from?
首先请告诉我，这种兴趣从何而来？
Why is it something that you have spent so much time and
为什么你会在这方面投入如此多的
energy and effort on?
时间、精力和努力？
ABELSON: So part of it quite frankly was this accident
ABELSON: 其中一部分，说实话是机缘巧合，
about going over to the AI Lab, meeting
那次偶然去 AI 实验室并在
Papert in the elevator.
电梯里遇到 Papert。
But again, also the sense that I think a lot of people have
但又说回来，也是因为那种很多人
of the joy of explaining things.
都有的、解释事物的乐趣。
And then the particular thing about--
然后特别的一点是——
well, for me it's computers and educational technology.
嗯，对我来说，就是计算机和教育技术。
It's not just explaining things.
不仅仅是解释事物。
It's empowering people to do them.
而是给人们去这样做的能力。
So even going back to the original sort of Logo turtle,
所以即使回到最初的 Logo 海龟，
which is the first thing I worked on, it's not that oh,
那是我参与的第一个项目，不是说
it's sort of cool.
“哦，这挺酷的”。
You might think about geometric designs.
你可以用来思考几何设计。
But I can make this world where students can kind of
但我可以创造这样一个世界，在其中学生
explore and do things that are both unexpected and
能探索，能做一些既出人意料
explainable.
又可以解释的事情。
And that's sort of the root of how I think about educational
这大致就是我看待
technology.
教育技术的本源。
But then there was a shift.
但是后来有了一个转变。
I guess for me it came--
我想对我来说，那是在——
oh, it didn't come until the late '80s or even the
哦，那要到 80 年代末，
mid-'90s, where I started thinking about the institution
甚至 90 年代中期，我才开始思考
in educational technology.
学校之于教育技术的意义。
There's this whole other ethic which is how should an
这是另一套伦理问题，教育机构在
institution behave in that world?
这个领域里，应该如何行事？
So it's not only about how you effectively transmit things to
所以这不仅仅关乎如何有效地将知识传授给学生，或者
students or do them.
实际去做这件事情。
It's what what's it mean for an institution to actually
而是，教育机构作为生存于世的
live in the world as a responsible citizen?
一个负责任的公民，意味着什么？
And I became really interested in that.
我对此产生了浓厚的兴趣。
The person who for me embodies that and still embodies that
对我而言，体现这一点、并且至今仍然体现这一点的人是
is Chuck Vest. His whole presidency was this sense of
Chuck Vest。他的整个校长任期都贯穿着这样一种思考：
is MIT acting as a responsible, ethical being in
MIT 在自身所能做的事情中，是否在扮演一个
what it can do?
负责任、有道德的角色？
So I think about educational technology in that way.
所以我是以这种方式来思考教育技术的。
It's not only how do we behave towards our own student body,
这不仅关乎我们如何对待自己的学生群体，
it's how do we behave towards the world?
还关乎我们如何对待整个世界？
So there is the sense that you often here of MIT, this sense
你经常会听到一种对 MIT 的看法，觉得
that MIT is a precious world resource.
MIT 是一项宝贵的世界资源。
And I certainly believe that's true.
我当然这么认为。
And then the question is, with terms of education and
那么问题是，在教育和
educational technology, how do you sort of step up to that
教育技术方面，你如何承担起
obligation?
相应的义务？
And part of it is how you behave as a
部分答案在于，你如何为
model for other places.
其他地方树立榜样。
So even going back to like the book that Gerry Sussman and I
甚至最早 Gerry Sussman 和我写的
wrote, there was always this sense that when you're writing
那本书，我们一直有种感觉，
a textbook at MIT, it's not really that they're going to
给 MIT 写教科书，并不会真的指望
be big sales about it, because in our case it was gosh, we're
能卖出很多，因为就我们那本书而言，老天，
teaching computer programming and it's got calculus in
我们是要讲计算机科学，而且
chapter one.
第一章还带着微积分。
How could you use that?
这书咋用？
But it's the sense of you're sort of writing it for the
但我们觉得我们是在为下一轮的
people who are going to write the next round of books for
作者写书，他们要写给
everybody else.
所有其他人看。
So a sense of people are watching and it
就有一种意识，人们在看着，
matters what you do.
所以你的所作所为很重要。
And that's kind of a little bit what's behind
这有点像 OpenCourseWare（开放课程）
OpenCourseWare.
背后的理念。
It's not just me.
不止我一个这样想。
The original notion about OpenCourseWare is we thought
关于 OpenCourseWare 最初的想法是，
that our audience in
我们认为开放
OpenCourseWare were other educators.
课程的受众是其他教育者。
And the way that whole initiative was crafted where
整个倡议构筑于一个想法上，就是
we said it's really important that we show all MIT courses
我们一定要展示 MIT 所有的课程，
because what you're trying to exhibit
因为你想展示的是，
there, your model was--
你的榜样作用是——
I'm very consciously--
我非常有意识地设想——
the education minister in some third-world country would like
某个第三世界国家的教育部长
to understand what that country should be doing about
可能想了解该国在化学工程领域
chemical engineering.
应该做些什么。
And then you sort of see displayed out before you is
然后你就能看到展示在你面前的
what MIT, the top institution in the world, thinks is
是 MIT，世界顶尖学府，
chemical engineering.
所理解的化学工程。
And this is what was in our heads when we made
这是我们在创立 OpenCourseWare 时
OpenCourseWare.
脑海中的想法。
Of course it didn't quite work that way because what we say,
当然，事情并没有完全像那样发展，
oh my god, they're all these people who actually want to
因为我们发现，老天爷，有那么多人
learn chemical engineering, who look at this stuff.
是真的想来学习化学工程，来看这些课程。
And that should have been obvious in hindsight because
事后看来这本应显而易见，因为
there are many more students in the world than educators.
世上的学生比老师多得多。
But we were surprised by that.
但当时我们很惊讶。
But to get back to the original ethos of that, is
但是回到最初的理想，
you're setting yourself up as a model and you're trying to
你是在把自己树立为榜样，
influence the influencers.
去影响那些决策者。
And what you do matters.
你的所作所为很重要。
And that's not only a technical obligation, it's an
而这不仅仅是技术上的责任，更是
ethical obligation for how you behave and how
一种伦理责任，关乎你的行为方式和
you think about it.
你对此的思考方式。
And that's kind of how I think about educational
这就是我对教育技术的
technologies.
看法。
It's with that sense of you're creating a model.
带着这样一种意识，你是在树立典范。
You have an obligation to sort of see that it works out right
你有义务确保它朝着正确的方向发展，
with respect to how you think the world is evolving and how
基于你对世界会如何演变、
you think the internet is evolving.
互联网会如何演变的理解。
But much, much of MIT is like that.
但 MIT 的很大很大一部分都是这样的。
It's a whole ethos of service that's really integral to how
这一整套服务精神对于这个
much of this community works.
社区的运作不可或缺。
INTERVIEWER: Tell me a bit more about the genesis of
采访者：再多跟我讲讲 OpenCourseWare 的
OpenCourseWare.
起源吧。
I know that when I first heard about it at the time it was
我知道当我第一次听说它的时候，也就是
first announced, I guess certainly not before then, it
在刚宣布它时，我想在那之前肯定没有，
was somewhat from my very limited perspective it seemed
从我非常有限的视角来看，MIT
very shocking that MIT would do that.
竟然会这样做，真是相当令人震惊。
And I'm just really interested in the genesis, the thought
我非常感兴趣于它的起源，在学校层面的
process institutionally, and also for you personally?
思考过程，以及对你个人而言是怎样的？
ABELSON: Yeah.
ABELSON: 是啊。
The only disappointment I have about OpenCourseWare is that
我对 OpenCourseWare 唯一的遗憾是，我们是
we announced it after the internet bubble had peaked.
在互联网泡沫达到顶峰后才宣布它的。
Again, if you go back to the late '90s, right, 1998, 1999,
又说回去，假如你回到 90 年代，对，
2000, there was this sense, if you read in the educational
1998，1999，2000，当时有一种观点，如果你
technology press or the education news, that
去读关于教育技术的媒体或者教育新闻，
universities were sitting on a gold mine.
说大学正坐在一座金矿上。
People talked about literally a $2 trillion economy coming
人们说大学可以带来实打实的 2 万亿
out of universities, taking their course materials and
美元的经济效益，把他们的教学材料
putting them on the network.
拿出来放到网络上。
And I just loved it that in that climate, MIT said hey,
而我非常喜欢的是，在那种气候下，MIT 却说，
we're giving it away.
嘿，我们不要钱。
Education is being part of the community of interacting and
教育应当是参与到这个互动地做研究的
doing research and being part of it.
社区，成为社区的一分子。
That's why you come to MIT.
那才是你来 MIT 的原因。
That stuff you can watch on television, we
那些你在电视上看到的东西，
just give that away.
我们免费赠送。
So I just loved saying that.
我非常喜欢这个说法。
Now that came from kind of a different place.
不过，这个想法源于一个略有不同的情景。
That was a wonderfully well-crafted story that fit
那是一个构思精巧的故事，和我们在那个
where we wanted to be in that place.
情景下希望能处于的位置非常契合。
But in fact what happened is Bob Brown, who was provost
但实际上发生的是，当时担任教务长的 Bob Brown
then, formed the Council on Educational Technology, which
成立了教育技术委员会（Council on Educational Technology），
he and I ran together for a couple years.
他和我在几年里共同主持这个委员会。
And that came from a prior thing, where as Chuck Vest
而那又源于更早的一件事，如 Chuck Vest
would say, he'd go around the country around 1997 and give
会说的，他在 1997 年左右
these talks.
在全国各地做演讲。
And people would say, there's this internet.
人们会说，现在有这个互联网。
What's MIT's going to do about it, quite literally?
MIT 对此打算怎么办，就这么直白地问？
And so was a sense of what MIT should do.
所以就有了一种 MIT 应该做什么的想法。
And a bunch of councils and groups met.
然后有一系列委员会和小组召开了会议。
There was a thing--
有一个叫——
I forget with the name was, but there was a council that
我忘了它的名字，但有一个委员会
sort of talked about MIT's agenda going ahead and talked
算是讨论了 MIT 未来的发展议程，
about all sorts of stuff.
讨论了各种各样的事务。
And they barely mentioned that there was an internet.
而他们几乎没有提到互联网的存在。
There was a phrase that said--
其中有一句话是——
literal phrase--
原话——
MIT should focus 02139.
MIT 应该专注于 02139（译者注：麻省理工学院的邮政编码）。
And there was this grudging idea that there was something
这里带着一种勉强承认的感觉，认为
outside in terms of the opportunities for MIT going
对于 MIT 未来的发展机遇来说，
forward in the future.
外面的世界还是有点什么的。
And then there was another committee which said the
然后另一个委员会持相反意见，由
opposite, that was run by Nick Negroponte and Mike Dertouzos,
Nick Negroponte 和 Mike Dertouzos 领导，
that basically said, gosh, MIT is the most wonderful
基本上是说：老天，MIT 是世界上
place in the world.
最棒的地方。
We should be expansive.
我们应该向外扩张。
And we should just take millions of dollars and invest
我们应该拿出数百万美元，
this in all sorts of technology things.
投资于各种技术领域。
And these two committees were kind of at loggerheads.
这两个委员当时算是僵持不下。
What kind of happened is the technology committee got
大致的情况是，技术委员会被
saddled with, you guys are just a bunch of technological
扣上了“你们就是一群
determinism.
技术决定论者”的帽子。
In this place, we don't have to think about it.
在我们这，我们不需要考虑这些。
The other committee said wow, this is really about the
而技术委员会则说，喔，这事实际
spirit of MIT.
关乎 MIT 的精神。
But there was tremendous dissatisfaction because it was
但人们对此非常不满，因为这
just ignoring the way the world was going.
完全忽视了世界的发展方向。
And so Bob Brown sort of wanted to find a way to
所以 Bob Brown 是想找个办法
mediate this stuff, to think about what's the way forward,
来调和这些分歧，在审视这些情况时，
looking at these things.
思考未来的路该怎么走。
And he formed the Council on Educational Technology, which
于是他成立了教育技术委员会（Council on Educational Technology），
it's kind of hidden agenda was to do that, find a path.
它多少有点隐藏的议题就是要这么做，找到一条出路。
So one of the things we did is we actually got McKinsey in to
所以我们做的一件事是，我们真的请来了
do a consulting--
麦肯锡（McKinsey）做咨询——
their standard kind of strategic consulting, saying
他们那种标准的战略咨询，
where we are we going, what are the opportunities?
说我们的方向是什么，有哪些机遇？
And we kind of said MIT is doing a whole bunch of
我们大致表示，MIT 正在做一大堆
disjointed things.
互不相关的事情。
One of the consultant's had a really nice graphic he made
其中一位顾问做了一张很漂亮的图，
with a whole bunch of sailboats
上面画着一大堆帆船，
that were MIT things.
代表 MIT 的各种项目。
And all the sailboats were going off in all kinds of
所有这些帆船都朝着
different directions.
各种不同的方向驶去。
And we did a survey of the MIT community
我们还对 MIT 社区做了一项调查，
about what's important.
关于“什么是重要的”。
And what was interesting is not coming from us on this ed
结果有趣的结论并不是来自我们
tech council, but as said back to us by the consultants, it
教育技术委员会，而是由顾问们反馈给我们的，
said, gee, what's really important at MIT is the
他们说，哎，MIT 真正重要的
integration of research and education.
是研究与教育的融合。
And now what's that say?
这意味着什么呢？
That says if you're thinking about distance learning in
这意味着，如果你从这个角度思考
this sense, if somehow that is just curriculum material and
远程教育，如果它只是讲课程材料，而
it's not infused with the notion of research, that's
没有融入研究的理念，那它就不算是
kind of not an MIT education.
MIT 式的教育。
So that one kind of fundamental they heard.
这是他们听到的一个基本点。
Another one they heard which this notion of
他们听到的另一个基本点是一体化
an integrated faculty.
教师队伍的概念。
So MIT, unlike lots of other places, has this
MIT 与许多其他地方不同，它有一个
notion of one faculty.
“统一的教师队伍”的概念。
We don't have graduate faculty or we don't have teaching
我们没有研究生导师，也没有教学教职
faculty and research faculty.
与研究教职之分。
We have faculty.
我们就只有教职员工。
And there's the sense if you're on the faculty, you're
并且有一种观念是，如果你在教师团队中，
supposed to do all of these things.
你就应该承担所有这些职责。
So there's this notion of if we really went and like oh,
所以我们的想法是，如果我们真的像
the Harvard Extension School, had a whole bunch of people
哈佛大学继续教育学院（Harvard Extension School）那样，
who are not actual Harvard faculty who were teaching this
让一大批不是真正的哈佛教师的人来讲课，
thing, ahh, that's not the sort of thing MIT does.
啊，那可不是 MIT 的做法。
So there were a bunch of principles like that.
于是就有了一系列这样的原则。
And eventually we were sort of saying as MIT goes forward, do
最终我们在讨论的是，随着 MIT 向前发展，
we think about expanding to new communities?
我们是否要考虑扩展到新的群体？
Right now we think of our potential student body as the
目前我们把潜在学生群体定义为排名顶尖，
top whatever it is, two percent, three percent of
大概是全球排名
students in the world.
前 2% 或 3% 的学生。
Should we be the top 10 percent?
我们是否应该面向前 10%？
So there was this notion of who we actually talk to?
进而有了这样的想法：我们究竟要与谁对话？
And we kind of strategically said we actually want to stay
从战略上我们大概说，我们实际上想留在
with the communities of people that we know.
我们所熟悉的人组成的社群里。
And we want to stay with an MIT of kind of style thing.
并且我们希望保持一种 MIT 的风格。
And that morphed into a thing that said we really want to
事情演变成，我们想要的是改变学生
change the dynamic of how a student interacts with MIT to
与 MIT 互动的模式，使其
something that can be lifelong.
成为一种终身的关系。
So there was this idea that right now you graduate MIT,
所以就有了这样一个想法，现在
and what it means basically means to be an alum is that
你从 MIT 毕业成为校友，基本上只
every year the Institute sends you requests for money.
意味着学院每年会向你发出捐款请求。
And we're saying shouldn't there be a different kind of
我们说，难道不应该有另一种
thing with that where you can participate in this community
形式吗，让你可以在智识上
intellectually for a long time?
长期参与到这个社区中？
So that was one of these things
所以那就是一种所谓的
called lifelong education.
“终身教育”（lifelong education）的东西。
And so out of that strategic thing, there came another
于是，在那一轮战略规划之后，产生了
thing, saying well, we kind of decided
另一个想法，说，好，我们大致
on that as the direction.
已经决定了这个方向。
Let's mush out this lifelong learning thing.
我们来把这个终身学习的概念具体化。
Let's figure out what it is.
我们来搞明白它到底是什么。
We actually did another consulting engagement with
我们实际上请来了 Booz Allen
Booz Allen, who came in as very analytical, saying is
做另一轮咨询，他们非常分析性地来，
this going to work?
讨论“这行得通吗？”
And basically after long drawn-out things and analyses
然后基本上在经过了漫长的过程，各种分析，
and talking to possible clients and competitors and
与潜在客户、竞争对手以及 MIT 内部
offices at MIT about everything, they found it
各办公室进行方方面面的沟通
wasn't going to work.
之后，他们发现行不通。
So they called in one of their spreadsheet ninjas, who made
于是他们找来了他们的一位电子表格高手，
this giant thing with every possible parameter you could
做了一个巨大的东西，包含了你能想象到的
imagine, what are the production values, how long is
每一个可能的参数，产品价值有哪些、
the course, what's the client thing.
课程多长、客户情况如何。
And basically it turned out that, I forget, if you've got
结果基本上是，我忘了，如果你有两万人
20,000 doing a course, you could kind of
上一门课，你或许能
a break-even, maybe.
勉强收支平衡，大概。
So this whole committee was actually pretty-- oh my god,
于是整个委员会当时都相当——老天爷，
what are we going to do?
我们咋办啊？
And finally, I think it was Dick Yue,
最后，我想应该是 Dick Yue，
there's some famous story--
有个很著名的故事——
I don't know if you talked to him.
我不知道你有没有和他聊过。
There's this famous story about he was
有个著名的故事说，他当时在
exercising or something.
锻炼身体还是什么。
And it sort of came to him about well, why don't we take
然后他突然灵光一现，诶，我们为什么不
this stuff and give it away.
把这些东西直接免费送人呢。
And that sounds like a crazy idea.
这听起来是个疯狂的想法。
But then you sort of think well you know, if we're not
但你接着会想到，好吧，
going to make money charging alumni and other people to do
如果我们无法通过向校友和其他人收费
this, maybe we can get foundations to pay for this.
来赚钱，也许我们可以让基金会来买单。
So it wasn't a totally crazy idea.
所以这也不完全是个疯狂的想法。
And then at the end of the summer what happened was the
那年夏末，委员会最终提交了
committee produced this report.
一份报告。
So that was the other thing that Dick did.
那是 Dick 做的另一件事。
MIT believes in data.
MIT 崇尚数据。
And he did this amazing thing, which is whenever the
他做了一件非常厉害的事情，就是
consultants would do anything, they'd interview somebody, and
每当顾问做什么事情时，比如要访谈某人，
he'd sort of xerox the sheet.
他就会把那张纸复印下来。
And he put it in this big notebook.
然后把它们装进一个大笔记本里。
And he had a notebook which was literally this high.
他那个笔记本，真有这么高。
And when he'd come in to make a presentation, he'd put the
当他来做报告时，他会把笔记本
notebook on the desk, saying the committee has done this
往桌上一放，说委员会做了这项研究，
research for its conclusions.
得出了这些结论。
And nobody would dare challenge him on that, despite
没人敢质疑他，尽管笔记本里
the fact that nothing in the notebook was relevant to what
实际上没有一样和他说的事情
he was saying.
有关系。
It was just a great, great ploy.
这真是个非常非常妙的策略。
But it's again, engineer's culture.
但这也再次体现了工程师文化。
We like data.
我们喜欢数据。
But the committee's report was this incredibly precise
委员会的报告是一份极其精确、
reasoned out, spreadsheet-backed, financial
经过推敲、有电子表格支撑的
model thing about how we could do some for pay lifelong
财务模型，说明我们如何做一些付费的
learning things with careful analysis.
终身学习项目，分析得很仔细。
And then at the end, there was about two pages.
然后在报告的末尾，大约有两页纸的篇幅。
It said, and by the way, we have this other idea that we
它说，顺便提一下，我们还有另一个想法，
should just give it away.
我们应该干脆把这些免费。
And we'll call it OpenCourseWare.
我们会叫它 OpenCourseWare。
With no analysis or anything.
没有任何分析之类的东西。
And then to its tremendous credit, Chuck Bastian, Bob and
接着，极为难能可贵的是，Chuck Bastian（注：此处原文或为 Chuck Vest）、
Tom Magnanti got inspired by this and said yeah, this one
Bob 和 Tom Magnanti 受此启发，说，对，
seems right.
这个看上去靠谱。
And that's what actually started the path towards
这就是 OpenCourseWare
OpenCourseWare.
之路的起点。
And then there were a lot of talks with--
然后我们进行了很多沟通——
Chuck went and got money from the Hewlett and Mellon
Chuck 到 Hewlett 基金会和 Mellon 基金会那里
foundations.
筹到了资金。
And we did a bunch of things, talked with the
我们也做了一系列的事情，
faculty over the year.
在这一年里与教师们沟通。
But that's kind of how it started.
但事情大致就是这样开始的。
And again, it started in this world of MIT is going to be
再说一次，它始于这样一种世界观：
the exemplar.
MIT 要树立一个榜样。
So we weren't talking really about distance education.
所以我们当时谈论的其实并不是远程教育。
We weren't even thinking about the students who
我们甚至不是在为那些将要
were going to do it.
使用它的学生考虑什么。
We were thinking about here MIT is
我们考虑的是，MIT 要
exhibiting itself as a model.
把自己作为典范展示。
It was right for 2000.
这在 2000 年是恰逢其时。
And it sort of grabbed everybody's imagination.
它在某种程度上抓住了每个人的想象力。
And then it happened as you said, at exactly the time that
接着，正如你所说的，它恰好发生
lots of these other universities were saying wow,
在其他很多大学都在说“哇，我们
we're going to make tremendous money for this.
要靠这个赚大钱了”的时候。
There were lots of start-ups.
当时有很多创业公司。
I don't know if people noticed.
我不知道人们有没有注意到。
I once went back and looked.
我曾经回头去查过。
And there were lots and lots of places that when we did the
当我们进行最初的麦肯锡分析时，
original McKinsey analysis, were saying, oh god, these
有很多很多地方都在说，噢天哪，
people are starting.
这些人要开始了。
Their company is starting.
他们的公司正在起步。
Their university is doing stuff.
他们的大学在做这些事情。
None of them are in business anymore.
如今它们没有一家还在运营了。
And it was just great that we can be so
而作为 MIT，我们能如此
counter-intuitive as MIT.
反直觉地行事，这真的很棒。
A very MIT thing.
这是一件非常具有 MIT 风格的事情。
INTERVIEWER: Can you talk a bit about the faculty reaction
采访者：你能谈谈首次提出 OCW
when OCW was first floated as a concept.
这个概念时，教职员工的反应吗？
Supportive, not supportive, what was the response?
是支持，还是不支持，当时的回应是什么？
ABELSON: It was surprisingly supportive.
ABELSON：出人意料地支持。
And in fact Larry Bacow, who was chancellor then, basically
事实上，当时担任校长的 Larry Bacow 基本上说，
said, look, you cannot go ahead with this unless you
听着，除非你们真的、真的去和教职工
really go, really talk to the faculty.
沟通，否则这个项目无法推进。
So there was a group of about four or five of us who made
所以，我们有一个大约四五人的小组，
presentations to every single MIT department.
向 MIT 的每一个系做了演示。
And we listened to a lot of stuff.
我们听到了很多声音。
I'd say the predominant negative reaction was oh my
我得说，主要的负面反应是，
god, you want to take my class notes and put them out on the
天哪，你们要把我的课堂讲义拿到互联网上
internet for everybody to look at.
让所有人都看到。
They're not good enough.
它们还不够好。
And we got really good it saying hey, you're willing to
我们后来很擅长这样回答，嘿，你愿意把这些给
give this to MIT students who are paying $40,000 dollars a
MIT 的学生看，他们每年付 4 万美元
year to listen to you.
来听你的课。
And you don't think they're good enough to put out for
却觉得它们没有好到
free to other people to look at?
能给别人免费看吗？
So we learned to make interesting
所以我们学会了如何巧妙地
answers to those things.
回答这些问题。
But it was to me surprisingly positive.
但在我看来，整体反应出奇地积极。
What everyone was expecting was, oh my god, you're giving
大家原本预期的是，老天爷，你这是要
away my intellectual property.
把我的知识产权白送出去。
I mean there might have been five people who said that.
我是说可能有五个人这么说过。
But it was almost unheard of.
但那几乎是闻所未闻的。
It was much more than the other reaction I said: well
更多的是我提到的另一种反应：
god, you're showing my stuff in other than its pristine
唉老天，在我花了很长时间打磨
state after I've worked on the publication
出版稿件之后，你却要以不完美的
manuscript for a long time.
状态展示我的东西。
But it was just very, very popular.
但总的来说，它非常、非常受欢迎。
And it certainly helped that the administration was so
而且管理层对这件事非常明显地积极支持，
incredibly visibly positive about this.
肯定也起到了很大帮助。
But again OpenCourseWare got positioned.
所以话说回来，OpenCourseWare 确定了它的地位。
We made some adjustments, some tweaks in the way we told the
我们做了一些调整，我们在讲述故事的方式和
story and what we did.
具体做法上做了一些微调。
I frankly don't remember what they were.
老实说，我已经不记得具体是什么了。
But it was really very important to us that this came
但对我们来说至关重要的是，它最终
out as an expression of the MIT community.
是 MIT 社区整体的一种表达。
So it wasn't a administration driven,
它不是由行政部门推动的，
something, something, something.
诸如此类的东西。
It really was an expression of what the faculty wanted to do.
它确实表达了教职员工想要做的事情。
INTERVIEWER: So you talked about OpenCourseWare as one
采访者：你刚才谈到把 OpenCourseWare 作为
example of MIT or what MIT does being an exemplar.
MIT 或者说 MIT 的行为方式的一个典范。
Ten plus years out, what has OCW's impact been on the
十多年过去了，OCW 对更广泛的世界
broader world?
产生了什么影响？
ABELSON: Oh, well OCW created what's called
ABELSON: 哦，OCW 开创了所谓的
Open Educational Resources.
开放教育资源（Open Educational Resources）。
So there is now an enormous I want to say movement that's
所以现在有一个巨大的，我想称之为运动,叫做 OER，
That word started at a UN conference which was talking
这个词源于一次联合国会议，讨论了
about OpenCourseWare and some more things.
OpenCourseWare 和一些其他事情。
That's where the word got coined.
这个词就是在那里创造出来的。
And it got elevated to--
随后它被上升到——
I forget what the phrase is-- how do you think about
我忘了具体措辞——如何思考
education and the internet to improve the state of humanity?
教育和互联网，以改善人类的状况？
And really a very long thing.
那是一段很长的表述。
But now there's an enormous, enormous whole open
但现在已经有了一个规模极其、极其
educational resources movement.
庞大的开放教育资源运动。
You've got to remember when OpenCourseWare started, there
你得记得，在 OpenCourseWare 刚起步的
was not the idea that universities at scale would
时候，还没有想法说，大量的高校
put educational material on the internet for free.
会把教育材料免费放到互联网上。
And now that's, well sure, ho hum.
而现在已经变成，嗯当然了，有什么好奇怪的。
So it caused just a major change in the
所以，它极大地改变了
way people did it.
人们的做法。
And it was a combination of that the time was kind of
这是时机正好、技术成熟，
right for it, the technology was right for it.
结合到一起的结果。
But also MIT put its institutional
也因为 MIT 为这个想法赋予了
imprimatur on that idea.
其机构权威的背书。
So it's been enormous.
所以它的影响是巨大的。
And not all of it identifies itself as universities.
并非所有参与者都自称是大学。
And not all of it identifies itself as
也不都会标榜自己是
certainly MIT or something.
MIT 或者什么的。
But just the idea that you can now go to the internet and
但你如今可以上网找到大量
find a lot of educational material, that's what
教育材料，这个观念是由
OpenCourseWare started.
OpenCourseWare 开创的。
INTERVIEWER: What do you see as the
采访者：你认为这场运动的
future for that movement?
未来会如何发展？
ABELSON: So this is something that we think about a lot with
ABELSON: 这是我们在 OpenCourseWare 以及像
OpenCourseWare and a lot from places like Creative Commons.
Creative Commons 这样的地方经常会思考的事情。
I kind of want to say it's done.
我有点想说，它已经完成了使命。
Again, I have to say there really was a question, right,
刚才说了，在 2000 年左右，
in 2000, about whether there could be a lot of free
确实存在一个问题说，互联网上是否能够
educational material on the internet.
有大量免费的教育材料。
It really was a question.
那确实曾是个问题。
Now it's not.
现在已经不是了。
And in a sense that's kind of happened.
某种意义上，这已经成为现实。
So the real future now is how do you make
所以未来真正在于，如何让
that stuff more usable?
这些材料更具可用性？
There's no sense of all the quality of it.
现在缺乏对其质量的整体认知。
There's no sense that I can really get certification that
也没有一个概念说，我能够从中
comes from it.
获得认证。
There's no real sense of how it fits together.
也不清楚这些材料如何整合在一起。
There's no sense of gosh, here are three different
也不清楚比如说，这里有三份不同的
presentations of diffraction.
对衍射的讲解。
How do they compare?
如何比较它们？
Which one should I use?
我该用哪一个？
So at the moment what's happening it's a tremendous
所以目前的情况是，有海量的
amount of raw material that has not very
原始材料尚未得到
effectively been mined.
非常有效的挖掘。
And what's happening now is there are lots and lots of
在当下，有许许多多的非营利公司和
both nonprofit companies and for profit start-ups that are
营利性初创企业正在尝试
trying to mine that in some effective way.
怎么有效地发掘它。
Nobody's cracked it yet.
还没有人破解它。
But that's where it needs to go.
但这正是必须前进的方向。
And it's kind of hard problem because it's one thing to
这是个难题，因为在网络上发布
publish a lot of material on the network.
大量材料是一回事。
But when you start talking about real education, you're
但当你开始谈论真正的教育时，
talking about interaction with people and empowering groups
你谈论的是与人的互动、赋予群体做
to do stuff, thinking about did people actually learn the
某事的能力，思考他们是否真的学会了，
stuff, do you certify it, how do you certify it,
要对它做认证吗，怎么
how do you use it?
做认证，怎么使用它？
So it's a lot harder work.
所以这是一项艰巨得多的工作。
And that's where the movement has to go.
这正是这场运动必须前进的方向。
INTERVIEWER: So you mentioned that a lot of that's
采访者：你提到有很多问题
unresolved.
尚未解决。
But are there directions or ideas that you have in terms
但是，你有没有一些方向或想法，关于
of making this material more usable or things that need to
如何让这些材料更好用，或者有哪些
be addressed?
问题需要解决？
ABELSON: Oh sure.
ABELSON：噢，当然。
I mean me and a thousand other people.
我是说，不只是我，还有成千上万的人。
They're all sorts of elements to it.
这里面有各种各样的要素。
Can I find something?
我能找到某个东西吗？
If I want to go find an explanation of magnetism
如果我想找一份非常适合初二学生的
that's really good for eighth graders, can I find that?
对磁力的解释，我能找到吗？
There are lots of places that are working on that.
有很多地方正在致力于解决这个问题。
Google is working on that.
Google 在做这个。
Creative Commons is working on that.
Creative Commons 在做这个。
Lots and lots of places doing that.
很多很多地方都在做这个。
The other one is how do you bridge the gap between even
另一个问题是，如何弥合哪怕是商业
for profit textbooks and this open stuff?
教科书和这些开放资源之间的差距？
Or to say it another way, if there's a lot of open stuff,
或者换种说法，如果现在有了大量的开放资源，
there are a lot of people who are starting companies that
有很多人在创办公司说，嗯，这其中
say well, what's the missing piece in that, that I can add
还缺少什么环节是我可以补充进去，
that'll be a sustainable business.
从而形成可持续的商业模式的？
And sometimes it's certification and sometimes
有时是认证，有时是
it's editing of the things and sometimes it's organization
内容编辑，有时是组织管理，
and sometimes it's adding some special videos or
有时候是增加一些特别的视频
something to it.
或其他内容。
People just exploring that all over the map.
人们正在各个领域探索。
That really is the big thing in educational
这确实是当前教育技术领域的
technology right now.
大热点。
There are textbook companies that say how do I make a
有些教科书公司会说，我怎样才能把
mixture of the stuff I hire people to write things, but
东西混合起来，一边是花钱请人编写的
also back on to all of this open stuff?
内容，一边倚靠所有这些开放材料？
So there's not going to be one answer.
所以不会有一个单一的答案。
And I think there's going to be an explosion over the next
我认为在接下来的五年里，会出现
oh five years, of people trying lots and lots of
一个爆发性的增长，人们会尝试很多
different things.
很多不同的事物。
And who knows?
谁知道呢？
It might converge on something after a while.
过一段时间，它可能会收敛到某种东西上。
INTERVIEWER: So you've been involved in obviously other
采访者：显然你还参与过其他一些非常
initiatives as well that are very, very significant,
非常重要的项目，iCampus 是
iCampus being one, DSpace.
其中之一，还有 DSpace。
Talk a bit about those.
谈谈这些项目吧。
And I'm kind of lumping them together, just part in the
只是因为时间关系，我把它们
interest of time.
放在一起问了。
But I'm going to let you sort of tell me what you think are
但我想请你讲讲，你认为哪些是
the most significant?
最重要的？
And maybe just sort of wrapping it in the larger
也许可以把它包在一个更大的
question of how technology has changed and continues to
问题里，技术是如何改变了、
change the classroom experience?
会如何继续改变课堂体验？
ABELSON: So sort of big area.
ABELSON：这确实是个相当大的领域。
INTERVIEWER: Yeah.
采访者：是的。
And we can take it in pieces, if that's easy.
我们可以分几个部分来谈，如果那样容易些。
ABELSON: So DSpace is kind of not
ABELSON：所以 DSpace
really about the classroom.
其实并不与课堂有关。
But it's one I like to talk about because that one's
但我想讲的是它，因为它是那个
actually strategic.
有战略意义的。
That was actually--
它实际上--
I almost want to say crafted by Ann Wolpert, who's the head
我几乎想说，是由图书馆馆长 Ann Wolpert
of libraries, and me, having to do with the issue of, will
和我共同精心设计的，涉及的问题是，
the public be able to get access to university research?
公众是否能够获得大学研究成果的访问权？
So OpenCourseWare is about this vision of the educational
OpenCourseWare 的愿景是让世界上
materials of the world's greatest institutions are
最伟大的学府们的教育材料
available to all of humanity.
能对全人类开放。
DSpace is about the vision of are the research let's say
DSpace 的愿景是，世界顶尖研究
products of the top research enterprises in the world
企业的研究成果，或者说产品，
available to all of humanity?
是否应当向全人类开放？
It's that vision.
是这个愿景。
And then you sort of want to say well okay, well it's easy.
然后你会想说，好吧，这很简单。
In fact, we should just post this on the internet.
实际上，我们只要把它发布到互联网上就行了。
And then you say why not?
然后你会问，为什么不呢？
And then you find that there's no sense of gosh, what's it's
然后你会发现，并没有一个清晰的认识说老天，
mean to post it on the internet?
把东西发布到互联网上意味着什么？
Is there a trusted place that has a pedigree in putting my
有没有一个值得信赖的、声誉良好的
research materials out in a way that they're going to be
地方，能以一种妥善的管理方式
proper stewardship of those?
发布我的研究材料？
And so we said one place to do that is
于是我们说，有个地方能做
the research libraries.
这件事，就是研究机构的图书馆。
So the libraries of the top research institutions could
所以，顶尖研究机构的图书馆可以
fulfill that role.
承担这一角色。
And DSpace was really about that.
DSpace 就是为了这个目的。
This was very early.
那是很早期的事情。
And it was kind of saying well look, we see-- when was this,
它大概是在说，你看，我们看到——这是什么时候，
1999 or something?
1999 年左右？
We kind of see this thing brewing with the ability to
我们看到，从我们能在互联网发布内容开始，
put stuff on the internet.
它就在酝酿之中了。
And we see this is going to be coming more and more of a
我们预感到这将成为一个
controversial flash point thing.
越来越有争议的引火点。
We were absolutely right about that.
我们对此的判断完全正确。
And we said what's missing from that is the notion that a
我们说，这里面缺少的是这样
university research library could be a place that a
一个概念，大学研究图书馆可以成为
research scientist would trust as a place to
研究科学家信任的场所，用于
look around the internet.
探索互联网上的资源。
So DSpace was about creating that.
DSpace 的目标是创造这样一个地方。
And that's happened to a large extent.
这很大程度上已经成为现实了。
It needs to happen a lot more.
但还需要进一步普及。
We're now in the interesting stage of that where the
我们现在正处于一个有意思的阶段，
publishers and journals are fighting back.
出版商和期刊开始反击了。
So you know the famous Gandhi thing.
你知道甘地的那个名言。
First, they ignore you.
起先，他们无视你。
Then they laugh at you.
然后他们嘲笑你。
Then they fight you.
接着他们攻击你。
Then they lose.
最后他们输了。
So we're sort of starting to get into then
我们现在有点开始进入
they fight us stage.
“接着他们攻击我们”的阶段了。
But I have a lot of optimism that'll work out.
但我对此非常乐观，相信会成功的。
So DSpace is not particularly about the classroom.
所以 DSpace 与课堂没有特别直接的关系。
But the classroom stuff is a very, very complicated mix
但课堂教学是一个非常、非常复杂的
because part of what you want to think about is making it
混合体，因为一方面你想让它具有扩展性，
expansive, making this world of sharing, making this world
创造一个分享的世界，创造这个让这些事情
where stuff is very possible.
都很可能实现的世界。
But at the same time, you want to think about what's really
但同时，你也要思考 MIT 真正的
special about MIT.
独特之处是什么。
What's the stuff that I want to do in my class that I
什么东西是我在自己的课堂上想做，
really don't want to share, because I want to say to these
但真的不想分享出去的，因为我想对这些
students, my god, you're not just in any place.
学生说，老天爷，你们可不是在随便一个什么地方。
You're at MIT.
你们是在 MIT。
And this thing that's happening in this classroom
此时此刻在这个教室内的事情，
now is really about our small group.
是关于我们这个小群体的。
And it's personal things.
是个人化的事情。
And I don't know where that ends out.
我不知道这最终会走向何方。
But I think both of those things are
但我认为这两种
happening at the same time.
情况在同时发生。
And so that ends up being a whole bunch of different kinds
于是就产生了各种不同类型的倡议，
of initiatives that look at that in different ways.
以不同的方式看待这个问题。
So one of them is the thing we funded under the Microsoft
其中之一是我们在微软 iCampus 联盟资助下的
iCampus Alliance, which is the notion of remote laboratories,
项目，即远程实验室的概念，也就是最初由
the iLabs thing that initially started with Jesus del Alamo
电子工程系的 Jesus del Alamo 发起的
in electronic engineering that said, gosh, I'm doing these
iLabs 项目，它说，老天，我给
labs for MIT students who are taking this thing.
修这门课的 MIT 学生做这些实验。
And just think about what it takes to a lab.
想象下做一个实验需要些什么。
You come in, and you have to spend 30 minutes setting it
你走进来，先花 30 分钟
up, and the equipment's broken, and you have to go
做准备，结果设备坏了，
through the safety class to make sure you don't do things.
你还得参加安全课程以确保你不会做错事。
When the reality is, you're just doing a three minute
而实际上，你只是要做一个
experiment.
三分钟的实验。
Wouldn't it be nice if you could do that from your dorm
如果你能通过互联网在宿舍里完成它，
room over the internet?
不是很好吗？
And that was sort of where Jesus's his vision of that
这就是 Jesús 在开创这个电路
started in the circuits course.
课程时所抱有的愿景。
And then we sort of said yeah, once you do that, once you can
然后我们想，是啊，如果能做到这一点，你就能
be across the campus, hey it's on the web.
跨越校园，嘿，因为它就在网上。
It could be across the world.
它可以跨越整个世界。
So there's this view of can you take those real laboratory
于是就有这样一种设想，能否把真实的
experiences and in a sense make them accessed remotely?
实验室体验，某种意义上实现远程访问？
So that's a little bit of trying to bridge this, hey,
所以这有点像试图弥合这种“嘿，它很特别，
it's special, but it's also accessible kind of thing.
但人们也能拿到它”的矛盾。
The stuff that I'd love to be playing with now is how you do
我现在很想尝试的东西是如何进行
like remote tutoring?
比如远程辅导？
How do I make it so if I'm in some kind of laboratory or
我怎样才能做到，如果我在某种实验室
some kind of classroom session where I'm getting individual
或某种课堂环节中接受个别指导，
instruction, you could also imagine doing that
你也可以设想从世界另一端
from across the world?
来做同样的事情？
Those are some of the things that I'm trying to think about
这些是我目前正试图与教育技术
with the ed tech council right now.
委员会一起思考的问题。
And then at the same time there's the evolution of
同时，还有像如何演进 OpenCourseWare
OpenCourseWare like things.
之类的事情。
We're sort of moving to a new stage in that where the idea
我们正进入一个新阶段，现有的这种“互联网
that there's effectively a book on the internet, well
上本质上有一本书”的想法，
that's good.
这很好。
But people want more.
但人们想要的更多。
And we have to think about what the next stuff is.
我们必须思考下一步是什么。
INTERVIEWER: So given that so much of this revolves around
采访者：既然这么多事情都围绕着
remote learning--
远程学习——
iLab or OpenCourseWare--
无论是 iLab 还是 OpenCourseWare——
what is the actual role of the physical location of the
那么，教室的实体空间，以及与
classroom and the class that gets together with a faculty
教师或讲师聚在一起的课堂，在
member or an instructor going forward?
未来实际上会扮演什么角色？
ABELSON: Yeah.
ABELSON：是啊。
What an incredibly good question.
这个问题问得太好了。
Right.
对。
Because again on the one hand, there are some places in
因为刚才说的，一方面，在教育中有
education, not the large lecture or anything, where you
一些场合，不是那种大型讲座之类的，
really, really, really want the sense of intimacy.
你会真的、真的、非常需要那种亲密感。
I mean as much as you could ever want, you really have to
我的意思是，做到什么程度都不为过，你真的必须表现出，
be, I'm here for you.
我在这里是为了你们。
I'm here for you students and we're doing this thing.
我在这里是为了你们这些学生，我们一起做这件事。
And we're engaged in this discussion right now.
我们此刻正投入于这场讨论中。
And I don't want this stuff going outside the classroom
我不想让这些东西流出课堂，
because what's happening with us right now is very special.
因为此刻我们的事情非常特别。
I'm telling you things that we just don't--
我正在告诉你们一些我们根本不会——
this is about us right now.
这是此刻仅属于我们之间的。
And that's really, really important and will be
这一点非常非常重要，而且
important forever.
永远都会重要。
The hard part is you have to ask yourself how much of that
困难之处在于你必须问自己，
sense of intimacy is technology now going to be
现在的技术能在多大程度上
able to supply?
提供这种亲密感？
And we're going to be figuring this.
我们将不断探索这一点。
Three years ago, it was a big deal to get on a video
三年前，能和别人进行视频会议
conference with somebody.
还挺了不起的。
And I do that with people across the world from my
而现在我和世界各地的人在我的办公室里
office and it's no more than sending a note saying hey, are
做这事，不过就是发条消息说，嘿，你现在
you on Skype now?
在 Skype 上吗？
Let's connect.
我们连一下吧。
And we have a conversation.
然后我们就交谈起来。
You have to ask yourself well, what are you losing by not
你必须问自己，没有亲临现场让
being physically present there?
你失去了什么？
And there's just a lot of research on that.
关于这一点有大量的研究。
They're all these shared
比如那些共享
conference spaces or something.
会议空间之类的。
I don't think people have done enough of thinking about that
我认为人们在教育和研讨会等方面
with respect to education and seminars and things.
对这个问题的思考还不够。
But sure, people are going to try it.
不过当然，人们会尝试的。
And we're going to find out.
我们会找到答案。
A lot of people feel like they're a little scared to go
很多人有点害怕朝那个方向
there because the implications of that is that maybe the
发展，因为这意味着也许实体
physical thing doesn't matter for that.
的东西对此来说并不重要。
And then you say well, that wasn't the important part
然后你会说，好吧，实体空间
about the physical location.
重要的部分不是那些。
The important part about the physical location is that
实体空间重要的部分在于
you're hanging around in the same place.
你们在同一个地方共处。
There are all these serendipitous things that
会有很多不期而遇的事情发生，
happen, what do they call it, the water cooler effect.
他们叫什么来着，饮水机效应。
And that's the really important thing about having a
那才是拥有实体空间真正重要
physical location.
的地方。
And then you sort of say, well you know there are these
然后你会说，嗯，其实
people who are working on that too.
也有人在研究这些。
And you have some stuff and you can counter people.
有一些东西让你可以与人互动。
There have been all these experiments with virtual
已经有各种各样对虚拟世界的
worlds, which seem to had a lot more pizazz three years
尝试，三年前它们似乎比现在
ago than they do now.
有活力得多。
But you're going to find technology being able to do
但你会发现，技术能够实现其中的
pieces of that.
一些部分。
And I don't know, we're going to find out which versions of
我也不知道，我们会弄明白其中哪些
that were important.
形式是重要的。
We can all make up science fiction stories about how
我们是可以编造科幻故事说，
physical presence doesn't matter.
实体到场并不重要。
But the point is for at least right now, physical presence
但重点是，至少在目前，
matters a whole hell of a lot.
实体到场相当重要。
And we'll sort of piece together the things that make
我们会拼凑出哪些东西是核心而
it work and are necessary and which can be supplanted.
必要的，哪些是可以被取代的。
INTERVIEWER: So I want to return too to something that
采访者：我还想回到你不久前
you said not too long ago about sort of that point when
提到的一点，就是当你开始
you started thinking about how MIT as an institution deals
思考 MIT 作为一个学院如何
with these kinds of questions.
应对这些问题的时候。
And I guess my question is, given this very thorny
我觉得我想问的是，鉴于我们
question that we were just discussing, how should MIT
刚刚讨论的这个非常棘手的问题，MIT
deal with that?
应该如何应对？
How should MIT going forward, thinking about the next five,
MIT 如何前进，展望未来五年、十年或
10, whatever years, deal with this very, very important
更长时间，来处理这个非常非常重要的
question of the classroom versus remote learning?
“课堂教学与远程学习”之争的问题？
And is it technology driven, is it policy driven, is it a
是技术驱动的，是政策驱动的，还是
combination?
两者的结合？
ABELSON: I kind of want to say it's ethically driven.
ABELSON：我有点想说，是由道德驱动的。
I really do feel that MIT has an almost ethical obligation
我真的觉得 MIT 有一种近乎道德上的义务去说，
to say look, we are a precious resource.
看，我们是一项宝贵的资源。
We understand about learning and technology and things.
我们理解学习和技术等相关事物。
I hate to sound maudlin.
我不想说得那么煽情。
We have an obligation to humanity to make that better.
我们对人类负有责任，去改善它。
And what's the way in which MIT can be an exemplar of that
而 MIT 如何能成为这方面的
and a model of that?
典范和榜样？
And it means that when you think about what we should do
这意味着，当你思考我们应该在
in educational technology at MIT, you really are thinking
MIT 的教育技术方面做些什么时，
that you're a model for the rest of the world.
你实际上是在考虑做全世界的榜样。
And how would you like that to happen?
你希望怎样做到它？
How would you like to play out?
你希望事情如何展开？
When we do something great in a classroom, we are obligated
当我们在课堂上做一些很棒的事情时，
to say how can other people follow that or how could other
我们有义务说，其他人如何效仿，或者如何分辨
people think about whether it's a good thing to do.
这是否是一件值得做的好事。
It's not just about MIT.
这不仅仅关乎 MIT。
It's a world resource that those of us who are teaching
它是一项世界性的资源，我们这些从事教学的人
are just privileged to be part of.
只是享有特权来参与其中。
And that privilege is not only about MIT undergraduate body.
而这种特权不仅仅关乎 MIT 的本科生群体。
It's about how the world is going to look at it.
而是关于世界将如何看待它。
So that doesn't tell you what to do but it's the sense of
这不会直接告诉你该怎么做，但是
obligation that you feel in doing that, that it's not just
这样想会带给你一种责任感，不能
looking inward.
只关注内部。
There are places that are not like that at all.
有些地方完全不是这样的。
I mean Harvard by and large is not like that.
我是说，哈佛大学大体上就不是这样。
But MIT is the sense of god, we're doing it for the world.
但 MIT 的感觉是，老天，我们是为了世界而做这件事的。
And that's how I think about the institutional thing when
这就是我在开展教育技术工作时
we do educational technology.
在学院层面的思考。
INTERVIEWER: This isn't about the classroom specifically,
采访者：这个问题虽然不是专门关于课堂的，
but it very much relates to what you just said.
但与你刚才所说的密切相关。
I wanted to ask you about the open access policy.
我想问一下关于“开放获取政策”（open access policy）的问题。
ABELSON: Oh, right.
ABELSON：哦，对。
That threads through lots and lots and lots of this.
它贯穿了访谈里的很多很多事情。
I talked before about DSpace.
我之前谈到了 DSpace。
So that's open access.
那就是“开放获取”。
I'm also one of the founding directors for the Free
我还是自由软件基金会（Free Software Foundation）的
Software Foundation, which is--
创始董事之一，这——
again growth, we talked before about the AI Lab culture.
同样生长于，我们刚才聊过的 AI 实验室的文化。
It grows right out of that.
它就是从那里孕育而生的。
That it's about a community thing.
它关心的事情是社区。
And the precious thing is that you allow people to build on
它宝贵之处在于，你让人们能在彼此工作的
each other's work.
基础上继续创造。
So a lot of times when people talk about open access, they
很多时候，当人们谈论“开放获取”时，他们
say gee, I ought to be able to read some stuff on the
会说，哎呀，我应该能够在互联网上读到
internet or be able to do stuff or it's locked away and
一些东西，或者做到一些事情，结果它被锁起来了，
I shouldn't have to pay to get it.
我不应该付费才能拿到它。
That's not the spirit, that's not the soul of it.
那不是它的精神，那不是它的灵魂所在。
The soul of it is that we can build a shared thing together.
它的灵魂在于我们可以共同创造一个共享的东西。
I always use the metaphor of there was this thing that
我总是用一个比喻，中世纪发生过这样
happened in the Middle Ages where the whole town together
一件事，整个城镇的人聚在一起，共同
got and built the cathedral.
建造了一座大教堂。
And I sort of think about the information environment as the
我某种程度上把信息环境看作是
opportunity to make that kind of cathedral.
建造那种大教堂的机会。
That humanity as a whole gets smarter because we can rebuild
人类作为一个整体会变得更加聪明，因为我们能够
what each others are doing.
重建彼此正在做的事情。
And we can build on it.
而且我们可以在其之上继续创造。
So that's for me, what open access is about.
所以对我来说，这就是“开放获取”的意义所在。
That's what OpenCourseWare is about.
这也是 OpenCourseWare 的意义所在。
So it's critical if you look at the license behind
所以有一点至关重要，如果你去看 OpenCourseWare
OpenCourseWare or free software, any of it.
或者自由软件背后的许可协议，无论哪一个。
One of it is that people get to use it how they want.
其中一点是，人们可以按照自己的意愿去使用它。
But the other is that people get to modify and we republish
但另一个是人们可以修改它，重新发布它，
it and make it better and improve.
让它变得更好，改进它。
So for me that's just central to what
对我来说，这就是人们所谓的
people call open access.
“开放获取”的核心。
Open access is in some sense a bad word because it doesn't
从某种意义上说，“开放获取”这个词取得不好，
have this sense of building on each other's work.
因为它没有体现出在彼此工作基础上创造的含义。
I'm sort of playing with this new slogan that I want to call
我最近在琢磨一个新口号，我想称之为
the remixed university.
“重混大学”（remixed university）。
That's the stage after just the open university.
那是在简单的“开放大学”之后的阶段。
It's not so interesting.
后者并没那么有趣。
I can go look at the classes that MIT teaches.
我是可以去看 MIT 开设的课程。
It's can that be a thing from which I can build even better
有趣之处在于，有没有可能让我以此为基础创造出来
stuff than MIT is doing.
比 MIT 在做的还要好的东西。
And that to me is just a central meme in how I hope the
对我来说，这是一个核心理念，我希望
internet continues to go.
互联网能按它来继续发展。
The internet started a lot of that.
互联网开创了很多这方面的事物。
Much of it's being threatened.
其中很大一部分正受到威胁。
But I think part of it is demonstrating to people the
我认为，这项工作里有一部分工作就是向人们展示
value of that.
这个理念的价值。
INTERVIEWER: So in talking or thinking a bit about your work
采访者：所以，在谈论或思考你在
in protecting the intellectual commons, you mentioned the
保护知识共享方面的工作时，你
Free Software Foundation, which is definitely something
提到了自由软件基金会，这肯定是
that I wanted to talk to you about.
我想和你聊的话题。
Tell me about Creative Commons, another I think
请讲讲 Creative Commons，我认为这是其中
important part of this.
另一个重要的部分。
ABELSON: Right.
ABELSON: 没错。
There was this magical couple years where we started DSpace,
有那么神奇的几年，我们启动了 DSpace，
we started OpenCourseWare, we showed Creative Commons, right
启动了 OpenCourseWare，展示了 Creative Commons，
around 2000.
大约在 2000 年左右。
So I had the tremendous fortune of actually working
我非常幸运能够与
with Larry Lessig.
Larry Lessig 共事。
We tried a joint course between Harvard and MIT when
当他正在构思一些关于开放文化等事物的想法时，
he was formulating these ideas about open culture and things.
我们曾尝试在哈佛大学和 MIT 之间开设一门联合课程。
And Creative Commons kind of started in a couple of
Creative Commons 算是始于几次
discussions, the sense of should there be something
讨论，关于是否应该在法律或
about sharing and commons that could happen in
政策方面做一些关于共享和
terms of law or policy?
公共领域的事情？
Larry had just recently unsuccessfully argued Eldred
Larry 当时刚刚在最高法院就
v. Ashcroft before the Supreme Court.
Eldred 诉 Ashcroft 案辩论失败。
So that was when Congress extended copyright
那是国会将版权期限又延长了
by another 20 years.
20 年的时候。
And that came up to the Supreme Court.
那件案子上诉到了最高法院。
And Larry argued at the Supreme Court and he lost.
Larry 在最高法院进行了辩论，但输了。
The Supreme Court basically said well, you may have shown that
最高法院基本上说，你或许证明了
this is a bad idea to extend copyright.
延长版权是个坏主意。
But by the way, it's Congress that makes the
但顺便一说，制定版权法的是
copyright law, not us.
国会，不是我们。
And Larry was looking for some constructive reaction to that.
Larry 当时正在对此寻找一些有建设性的回应。
I was thinking about some kind of way of rewarding people
我当时在思考一种方式，从实质上来
effectively for putting things into the public domain.
回报那些将作品放入公共领域的人。
What could you do by policy to stimulate
在政策层面，你可以做些什么
that kind of sharing?
来激发这种共享？
We talked about that.
我们讨论了这个问题。
Larry found some funding.
Larry 找到了一些资金。
And we got this idea of Creative Commons.
于是我们有了 Creative Commons 这个想法。
There were small group of about, I want to
我们有个小团队，大约有
say about 10 of us.
十个人左右吧。
And sort of said gee, what we want to do is in the phrase,
我们说，哎呀，我们想做的事情，用一句话概括，就是
brand the public domain.
“为公共领域打造品牌”。
We wanted people to be aware that the shared stuff that you
我们希望人们意识到，那些你可以使用和
can use and reuse was not sort of the detritus.
重用的共享资源并不是某种废弃物。
The law in the US talks about abandoning something to the
美国法律谈到将某物"遗弃"给
public domain.
公共领域。
It was not sort of this invisible stuff.
它不是这种没人注意的东西。
One of the things you can do on the internet is you can
在互联网上你能做的一件事是，你
actually give that an identity and make people aware of it.
可以给它一个身份，让人们意识到它的存在。
That was the soul of Creative Commons.
那才是 Creative Commons 的灵魂。
And then it kind of linked into some stuff that I'd been
然后它又和我与万维网联盟（WebConsortium）
doing with the Web Consortium that said oh by the way, one
合作的事情联系起来，
of the things you might want to do if you're going to make
说顺便一提，如果你要为这个
licenses crafted to that, you want to make those licenses
目的设计许可协议，你可能会想让
machine readable so machines can
机器能读取这些许可，
identify that on the internet.
以便机器能在互联网上识别它们。
So that's the start of Creative Commons.
这就是 Creative Commons 的起点。
And that program is sort of still going ahead.
这个项目目前仍在继续前进。
It's got a long, long, long way to go.
它还有很长、很长、很长的路要走。
I remember we were sitting around and saying well, what
我记得我们曾坐在一起讨论说，
would be success?
怎样才算是成功了？
How many things do you think should have these licenses?
你认为有多少东西应该采用这些许可协议？
So I'm always the poor non-visionary.
我总是那个缺乏远见的人。
Right.
对。
And I said, gosh if we got a couple of million of things on
我说，天哪，如果网络能有数百万个采用
the net with the Creative Commons, that
Creative Commons 的东西，
would be really good.
那就真的很不错了。
And Larry said well, I actually think all of it
而 Larry 则说，我其实认为所有内容
should be Creative Commons.
都应该采用 Creative Commons。
And then we seem to have compromised.
然后我们似乎折中了一下。
Now there's about 200 million Creative Commons
现在网上大约有 2 亿份采用
documents on the net.
Creative Commons 的文档。
So it will also hit a meme and expand it.
所以它也会成为一个热门的理念，然后扩展它。
And by the way, had a lot to do with OpenCourseWare.
顺便说一下，这与 OpenCourseWare 有很大关系。
So I was very active in the start up of both of those.
我在这两者的创立过程中都非常活跃。
And from the point of view of Creative Commons, MIT was the
从 Creative Commons 的角度看，
first sort of big, important place to adopt Creative
MIT 是第一个采用 Creative Commons
Commons licenses.
许可的重要机构。
And from the point of view of OpenCourseWare, we wanted
而从 OpenCourseWare 的角度看，我们
there to be a lot of freely licensed stuff on the web.
希望网络上有大量自由许可的资源。
So in particular when I put up my lectures on OpenCourseWare
特别是当我把自己的讲座放到 OpenCourseWare 上，
and I want to put some illustrations into my lecture,
并且想在讲义中加入一些插图时，我
there's a lot of Creative Commons licensed stuff that I
有大量采用 Creative Commons 许可的资源
could just use.
可以直接使用。
So that program still hasn't unfolded a lot.
所以这个项目还没有完全展开。
But it was very consciously--
但它是非常有意识地——
at least I thought about it.
至少我是这么想的。
I was working on those two things together.
我是在同时推进这两件事情。
INTERVIEWER: You mentioned that open access or the
采访者：你提到开放获取或
intellectual commons is under threat.
知识共享正面临威胁。
Can you talk a bit about that, the current environment now as
你能谈谈这一点吗，现在的环境与
opposed to when you were pioneering all of this?
你当初开创这一切时相比有什么不同？
ABELSON: Well like I said, we've gone from the stage of
ABELSON：嗯就像刚才说的，我们已经从
they ignore us to the stage where they laugh at us to the
“他们无视我们”的阶段，走过了“他们嘲笑我们”的阶段，
stage where they are actually fighting us.
到了“他们开始对抗我们”的阶段。
The rhetoric in Congress now is we're
如今国会里的论调是，
stealing all of this stuff.
我们在窃取这些东西。
Everybody is stealing stuff on the internet, that why don't
人人都在互联网上偷东西，你们为什么
you pay for it?
不为此付费？
Gosh, the US economy depend so much on intellectual property
天哪，美国经济如此依赖知识产权
and exporting that, we have to protect the
及其出口，我们必须保护网络
stuff on the network.
上的东西。
And the whole rhetoric is completely dominated by that.
整个论调完全被这种观点所主导。
I mean part of the problem is that Creative Common sounds a
我的意思是，部分问题在于 Creative Commons 听起来
lot like communist. So everyone says gosh, you guys
很像"共产主义"。所以每个人都说天哪，
are a bunch of communists.
你们这群人是共产主义者。
You want to steal our stuff.
你们想偷走我们的东西。
Oh my god, there was an article when Creative Commons
老天爷，Creative Commons 刚起步时有一篇
was first starting up, in was it Billboard, which talked
文章，在《告示牌》（Billboard）上，讲到老天，
about gosh, there is this young composer who puts his
有位年轻的作曲家把他的音乐放到了
music up on a Creative Commons thing.
Creative Commons 的平台上。
And this turned out to be a great hit.
结果它大受欢迎。
And now he can't get any monetary value to it because
现在他无法从中获得任何经济价值，因为他把它
he gave it away.
免费送出去了。
And he's dying of AIDS and can't pay for the medication
他快要死于艾滋病，却买不起他
that he needs.
需要的药物。
And you Creative Commons people are the ones who is
你们 Creative Commons 的这些人
responsible for this guy dying of AIDS.
就是导致他死于艾滋病的罪魁祸首。
And there's this whole rhetoric that's around it,
围绕这个事情有了这一整套说辞，
because people are starting to see that it's getting serious.
因为人们开始意识到事情变得严重了。
And you have a lot of business models that are simply based
有许多商业模式本身就是建立在
on the fact that you could control the
你能够控制分发渠道
distribution channels.
这一事实上。
So a lot of people think that those of us in Creative
因此，很多人认为我们这些参与 Creative
Commons are against copyright and against commercialism.
Commons 的人反对版权、反对商业主义。
And that's just not true.
完全不是这样的。
I mean Creative Commons is built in copyright.
我是说，Creative Commons 是建立在版权之上的。
And the thing that I think is bad is not that people are
我认为糟糕的事情不在于人们在
making money, it's that they're exerting over-control.
赚钱，而是他们在施加过度的控制。
So if there is a way to, without exerting that kind of
如果有一种方式，能在不施加那种控制的
control, realize money from this stuff, well great.
情况下，从这些东西中盈利，那很好。
I mean I love it if people say gee, we've got a business and
我很乐意如果有人说，我们有一门基于
it's working on Creative Commons stuff.
Creative Commons 的东西运作的的生意。
But maybe it's a service business.
也许那是一项服务型的业务。
Or maybe it's an advising kind of business or maybe it's some
或者也许是一项咨询类的业务，又
other spin where you use the free material to bolster the
或者是某种其他形式，利用免费材料来
fact that you're providing other stuff of value.
支撑你提供其他有价值的内容。
And I think that's where this stuff needs to go.
我认为那是这事情应当发展的方向。
But the particular thing that works is very sensitive to the
但哪种模式能奏效，很大程度上
state of technology of the web.
取决于网络技术的发展状态。
And that's evolving very, very fast. And it's just sort of
而技术的发展非常、非常快。所以这事
exploring more, exploring more business models.
就是不断探索，探索更多的商业模式。
But when I said people are fighting it, by and large
但当我说人们在与之对抗时，
you're seeing people in the old business models who of
大体上你看到的是那些旧商业模式中的人，
course are established, who of course have stories that
他们当然已经站稳了脚跟，当然有
Congress understands.
国会能够听懂的说辞。
So it's always hard when you're trying to make policy
所以当你试图制定政策并对未来可能的样子
and you have a vision of what could be.
有一个愿景时，事情总是很困难的。
A vision of what could be is never powerful compared to a
一个关于“可能会是什么”的愿景从来都不如一个关于
vision of what is.
“现在是什么”的视野那样强大。
And it just takes a long time.
并且这需要很长的时间。
INTERVIEWER: So in moving towards wrapping up just a
采访者：那么我们试着开始收尾，在
bit, in these two related but somewhat differing areas of
这两个相互关联但又有所不同的领域，
open networks, open access, and educational technology
开放网络、开放获取，以及聚焦于教育的
with a focus on this whole question of the remoteness or
远程属性或局域性这一整体问题的教育技术，
the locality of education, MIT has been obviously
显然 MIT 在历史上一直都是
historically a leader in both of those areas, if you think
这两个领域的领导者，如果你把
about OpenCourseWare as one example of many.
OpenCourseWare 视为众多例子之一的话。
What should MIT be doing looking ahead to continue to
MIT 在未来应该做些什么来继续保持领先地位和
lead and be ethical as you said?
道德准则，如你刚才所说的那样？
I mean are there things that MIT is not doing that it
我的意思是，有没有哪些事情是 MIT
should be doing or that it is doing that it
目前没做但应该做的，或者是正在做
should continue to do?
且应该继续做下去的？
ABELSON: So one of the things that MIT is not doing, and I'm
ABELSON：MIT 目前没在做的一件事是，
not sure why not, is we are currently making a lot of
我不确定为什么，尽管我们正与
partnerships with institutions around the world, which I
世界各地的研究机构建立大量合作关系，
think is fantastic.
我认为这非常棒。
But too often there is no educational piece in those
但在这些合作关系中，往往缺乏
partnerships.
教育的成分。
So we talk about MIT's association with some research
我们与某些研究机构谈论 MIT 的合作，
institute and partly because of what these other places
一部分出于这些其他机构想从 MIT
want from MIT and whether they view MIT, they sort of say
得到什么以及他们如何看待 MIT，他们会说
this is a great research partnership.
这是一个很棒的科研合作。
And one of the things MIT needs to be insisting on is
而 MIT 需要坚持的一点是，
what's the place of students and undergraduates in that
在这种合作关系中，学生和本科生的
kind of partnership?
位置在哪里？
MIT needs to say as part of leading the world, we deeply
MIT 需要声明，作为引领世界的一部分，
believe that what makes an institution like MIT work is
我们深信 MIT 这样的机构得以运作的
the integration of research and education.
关键在于研究与教育的结合。
MIT is not saying that strongly enough.
MIT 在这方面表达得还不够强有力。
And I think that's another place where MIT needs to lead.
我认为这也是 MIT 需要发挥领导作用的另一个地方。
It's saying how do you become a great institution?
是说，如何成为一个伟大的研究机构？
It's not only a good idea to be involved in education, but
参与教育不仅是个好主意，而且是
it's integral to what makes the place successful.
让这个地方成功的关键因素。
So there's a thing MIT is not doing right now, that I really
这是 MIT 目前没在做的事情，我真心希望它能在
wish it were going more.
这方面做得更多。
The other thing that I'm personally working on with the
我个人正在与教育技术委员会以及教务
Educational Technology Council and with the provosts is this
长们一起推进的另一件事，是
notion of opening the walls of the university in the sense
“打开大学围墙”的理念，这不仅仅是
that it's not merely let's say the OpenCourseWare vision or
指像 OpenCourseWare 或 DSpace 那样的
the DSpace vision that says MIT puts stuff out that allows
愿景，让 MIT 把东西
the world to participate.
放出去，让世界能参与。
It's that there's a way of taking stuff in.
而是要有办法把东西吸纳进来。
What role in terms of educational resources do our
在教育资源方面，我们的校友扮演
alumni play?
什么角色？
If you take the combined MIT alumni, which are what now,
如果把 MIT 校友加在一起，现在是多少，
80,000, 90,000, you have a considerable fraction of the
八万，九万？你就拥有了全球
technological power of the world.
科技力量中相当大的一部分。
How does MIT use that as a research for improving our
MIT 怎样能利用这一点来研究如何改进我们的
education and again creating a model of how top technology
教育，并且像刚才提到的，树立一个典范
people can contribute to institutions in the world.
来展示顶尖技术人才如何为世界上的研究机构做出贡献。
MIT is not doing that enough.
MIT 在这方面的努力还不够。
That's a little bit of what we're trying to work on now.
这是我们现在尝试解决的一部分事情。
In a world where, oh some university I want to mention
在这样一个世界里，我想提下
and say we could teach calculus to 50,000 people in
某所大学说我们可以给国外的五万人
some foreign country, how do we use technology to allow our
教微积分，我们如何利用技术让我们的
undergraduates to have tremendously good
本科生获得极佳的国际体验，
international experiences, while
同时还能修读
taking some MIT calculus?
MIT 的微积分课程？
Are there ways we can translate little pieces of MIT
是否有办法转化 MIT 的一小部分，
so that MIT students can have some of these experiences
让 MIT 的学生能够获得这些体验，
without feeling that they have to blow off
而不用觉得他们必须水掉
courses for a semester?
一整个学期的课？
The mechanical engineering department talks about
机械工程系在讨论，如果
wouldn't it be great if students in mechanical
机械工程的学生能休假两周，
engineering could take two weeks off and go build cars
去怀特岛造车并拿它们赛车，
and race them on the Isle of White.
那该多好。
How do we make that possible?
我们如何使之成为可能？
So that's a direction where I think MIT needs to go.
这是我认为 MIT 应当前进的一个方向。
I said there's this buzz word, the remixed university.
我刚才提到了一个流行词，"重混大学"。
How do we make that possible and how does MIT lead in
我们如何实现它，MIT 又如何在
showing how you can make that possible?
展示这种可能性方面发挥领导作用？
INTERVIEWER: I mean MIT obviously is a place with
采访者：我想说，MIT 显然是一个
tremendous technical technological expertise.
拥有强大技术专长的地方。
But our conversation has ranged over all sorts of
但我们的谈话涉及了各种各样的话题，
topics that go beyond simple technology, policy issues,
超越了单纯的技术、政策问题，触及到
just how we live our lives in the world.
我们在世界上如何生活。
And I'm wondering if you could talk a bit about what special
我在想，能否谈谈什么特殊或者特定的角色，
or particular role technologists, engineers
是技术人员、工程师在这些
should or could play in those broader ethical,
更广泛的伦理、哲学、政策类问题中，
philosophical, policy kinds of questions?
应该或能够扮演的？
ABELSON: Well, part is the easy thing about just knowing
ABELSON：嗯，一部分是比较容易的
the consequences or the likely consequences of certain kinds
事情，比如知晓某些投资或政策的后果
of investments or policies.
或可能的后果。
And I don't think anybody will argue that engineers and
我想不会有人反对，工程师和
scientists should speak up about that.
科学家应当就这些问题发声。
But I think beyond that there's this sense of actually
但我认为在此之上，还有一种"真正
making things, which I do think is very special to
去创造东西"的意识，我确实认为这是工程领域的
engineering.
独特之处。
It's really find to talk about things and to discuss, and
谈论事情，讨论、讨论再讨论，当然
discuss, and discuss, but at the end of the day you have to
很好，但归根结底，你必须要有
have some effect and some kind of impact.
一些实际效果，产生一些影响。
And engineers are great in doing things.
而工程师们很擅长实际行动。
It's not always right.
结果未必总是对的。
But there's this notion of you kind of have to put it on the
但有一种观念是，你必须承担风险，
line and make something.
做出一点东西来。
And that's part of what it means to, I want to say
我想说，参与“世界应该是什么样子”的
participate in the discussion of how the world should be.
讨论，就带着得去这样做的意味。
You come in and you actually think about how to make it.
你加入进来，你真正去思考如何实现它。
And you try it.
然后你去尝试。
And you never get it right the first time.
你永远不会一次就做对。
And then you make it better.
然后你把它做得更好。
And there needs to be that sense of instrumentality.
这其中需要有一种工具性的意识。
And that's what I think a place like MIT and a place
我认为这正是像 MIT 这样的地方，
like engineering cultures can add to these discussions.
以及工程文化，能够为这些讨论增添的东西。
And there needs to be a whole lot more of that.
我们需要更多大量这样的东西。
INTERVIEWER: Is there anything that you haven't had a chance
采访者：在我们即将结束之际，有没有什么
to talk about that we should have touched on as we're
你还没机会谈到，但我们本应该
wrapping up.
触及的话题？
ABELSON: Well no, other than I'm constantly humbled and
ABELSON：嗯，没有了，除了我始终对自己能有幸
amazed and charged by just the privilege of being in
身处 MIT 这样的地方感到受宠若惊，它如此惊艳，
a place like MIT.
让我充满动力。
I mean everybody talks about what a unique place it is.
我的意思是，大家都说这是一个多么独特的地方。
But there's just this personal sense of how in hell did I
但我个人总有一种感觉，我到底是
ever end up here, interacting with this group of people?
怎么能来到这里，与这群人共事的？
So I drive in from Newton every morning.
我每天早上从 Newton 开车过来。
And there's this place where you drive up Commonwealth
有一个地方，你沿着联邦大道开车，
Avenue and then you sort of turn and
然后你转弯，开过
go over the BU Bridge.
波士顿大学桥。
And the BU Bridge sort of looks like this gateway thing.
波士顿大学桥看起来就像是一个大门。
And I say, I can't believe it.
我会说，我简直不敢相信。
It's almost every day, after so many years, I say oh my
几乎每天，这么多年了，我都会说，老天爷，
god, I'm coming to MIT.
我要去 MIT 了。
How did I manage to do this?
我是怎么做到的？
How did I get so lucky as to be in a place like this, just
我是何其有幸能身处这样一个地方，
surrounded by all of these brilliant people and all of
周围全是这些才华横溢的人，
these incredible students?
这些出类拔萃的学生？
INTERVIEWER: Okay.
采访者：好的。
Well, thanks so much Hal.
那么，非常感谢你，Hal。
I really appreciate you taking the time to talk to us.
我真的很感激你能抽出时间与我们交流。
ABELSON: Sure.
ABELSON：不客气。
INTERVIEWER: It was wonderful.
采访者：这次谈话很精彩。
Thank you.
谢谢。